<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Catholicks defence for their adoration of the body and blood of our Lord as believed really and substantially present in the Holy Sacrament of the Eucharist.</title>
            <author>R. H., 1609-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66958</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12589812</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12589812</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63863</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66958)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63863)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 971:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Catholicks defence for their adoration of the body and blood of our Lord as believed really and substantially present in the Holy Sacrament of the Eucharist.</title>
                  <author>R. H., 1609-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Abraham Woodhead, who is in actuality R.H. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Real presence.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63863:1"/>
            <p>THE CATHOLICKS DEFENCE, FOR THEIR ADORATION OF THE Body and Blood OF OUR LORD, As believed Really and Subſtantially preſent IN THE Holy SACRAMENT OF THE EUCHARIST.</p>
            <p>At <hi>OXFORD</hi> Printed, <hi>Anno</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:63863:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63863:2"/>
            <head>THESES of Adoration of the <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CHARIST.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>PRoteſtant</hi>-Conceſſions. §. 1.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Catholick</hi>-Aſſertions. §. 1.
<list>
                     <head>Preſuppoſitions. §. 1.</head>
                     <item>1. Of a Precept of giving Divine Worſhip to our Lord. §. 1.</item>
                     <item>2. Of our Lord's whole Perſon its being where his Body is. §. 2.</item>
                     <item>3. Of this Divine Perſon being ſupremely adorable wherever his Body is: Granted by <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> §. 3.
<list>
                           <item>Not only in Virtue, but Substance. §. 5.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. That this Preſence of our Lord's Body and Blood is by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants affirmed in the Euchariſt; and that this Body is then to be worſhipped with ſupreme Adoration. §. 5.</item>
                     <item>5. Further affirmed; That Chriſt's Body and Blood are preſent not only to the worthy Communicant, but to the Symbols; and whilſt preſent are to be adored. §. 7.</item>
                     <item>6. Granted by <hi>Daille,</hi> That tho' he and his believe not Chriſt's Body preſent in the ſigns, yet they, for this, break not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with thoſe that hold it. §. 8.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:63863:3"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Catholick</hi> Aſſertions.</head>
                     <item>1. A Sign or Symbol to remain after Conſecration diſtinct from the thing ſignified. §. 9.
<list>
                           <item>This external Sign to be all, that which is perceptible by the ſenſes, of the Bread and Wine; tho' not their Subſtance. §. 10.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The word <hi>Sacrament</hi> to be taken not always in the ſame ſenſe, but ſometimes for the Sign or Symbol; ſometimes for the thing ſignified. §. 11.</item>
                     <item>3. Catholicks ground Adoration, not on Tranſubſtantiation, (which, as alſo Conſubſtantiation, involves it) but on Real Preſence with the Symbols: maintaining Adoration due, tho' Chriſt's Body were preſent, neither under the Accidents of Bread (as <hi>Catholicks</hi> ſay); nor under the Subſtance of Bread (as <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſay); but after ſome other unknown manner diſtinct from both. §. 17.</item>
                     <item>4. Suppoſing (not granting) Tranſubſtantiation an error, yet if Corporal or Real Preſence held by the Lutherans be true, Catholicks plead their Adoration warrantable. §. 18.</item>
                     <item>5. Suppoſing Real Preſence an Error, and the <hi>Lutheran</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Church both miſtaken; yet theſe latter, in ſuch Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as excuſable from Idolatry, as the other. §. 19.</item>
                     <item>6. Suppoſing both the former Opinions Errors, and (indeed) no Preſence of Chriſt's Body with the Symbols at all; yet ſuch Adoration by the one, or the other of Chriſt (who is a true object of ſupreme Adoration, and only miſtaken by them to be where he is not) cannot be termed ſuch Idolatry, as is the profeſsed worſhipping of an Object not all adorable. §. 21.</item>
                     <item>7. Whatever Idolatry it is called in a Manichean worſhipping Chriſt in the Sun, or in an Iſraelite worſhipping God in the Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> becauſe adoring a fancy of their own, (and a good intention grounded on a culpable ignorance excuſeth none from Idolatry;) yet ſince <hi>Daille,</hi> and perhaps others, allows a reaſonable (tho' miſtaken) ground of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſufficient for avoiding the juſt imputation of Idolatry;
<pb facs="tcp:63863:3"/>hence if Catholicks can produce a rational ground of their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending Chriſt preſent in the Euchariſt, tho' poſſibly miſtaken in it, they are to be excuſed from Idolatry, on the ſame terms. §. 22.
<list>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Catholicks</hi> Grounds for their Belief.</head>
                           <item>1. Divine Revelation. §. 24.</item>
                           <item>2. The Declaration thereof by the ſupremeſt Church-Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in Councils. §. 25.</item>
                           <item>3. The Teſtimony of Primitive Times. §. 26.</item>
                           <item>4. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Doctrine and Practice of the later, both Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches. §. 27.</item>
                           <item>5. <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Conceſſions. §. 28.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. For theſe Grounds given by <hi>Catholicks,</hi> Idolatry by many <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> of late but faintly charged upon the Church of <hi>Rome. §. 30.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>9. <hi>Catholicks</hi> grant, That to adore what is believed to be Bread, or perform the external ſigns of Adoration to our Lord as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent there, where the Worſhipper believes he is not, is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be done by any whilſt ſo perſwaded. §. 33.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise_on_the_Eucharist">
            <pb facs="tcp:63863:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63863:4"/>
            <head>CATHOLICK Theſes, Concerning the ADORATION of Chriſt's <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> IN THE EUCHARIST.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>1</label> COncerning the Adoration of Chriſt's Body and Blood, and ſo of his Divine Perſon, as preſent in the Euchariſt, 1. I ſhall ſhew, <hi>What in reaſon is or must be conceded by Proteſtants.</hi> 2. Examine <hi>what Catholicks maintain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſuppoſe a general precept of giving <hi>ſupreme and divine ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Christ:</hi> And,<note place="margin">Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> that as Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive precepts (ſuch as this is) do not oblige to every time, and place; ſo, if they are unlimited and general, they warrant the lawfulneſs of our practice of them in any time or place; nor is there any need of any particular divine command in reſpect of theſe (i. e. <hi>places</hi> and <hi>times,</hi>) without which command we may not obey them. [For, what abſurdities would follow hence? For, Was our Saviour, when on Earth, never lawfully worſhipped, but in place, or time, firſt commanded? Nor then, when he ſhewed and preſented himſelf to them for ſome other purpoſe, than for adoration? as to teach them, to ſuffer for them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Might not the <hi>Magi</hi> worſhip him lying in the Cratch, diveſted of all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Majeſty, without a ſpecial command from God?] But it is ſufficient to warrant our practice of them; if, in reſpect of ſuch time, and place, there be no expreſs prohibition.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>2</label> 2. I ſuppoſe; that, <hi>where-ever the Body of our Lord is, there is his whole perſon;</hi> it being no more ſince this Reſurrection to be a dead body, (for <hi>Chriſt dieth no more,</hi> Rom. 6.9.); but having the Soul joyned with it: as likewiſe, ever ſince the Incarnation, having alſo its <hi>hypostaſis</hi> or ſubſiſtence from the Divinity joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it; even when it was in the Grave, and the Soul ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63863:5"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>3</label> 3. I ſuppoſe, it is a thing granted alſo by learned Proteſtants, That, <hi>where ever this Body of our Lord is preſent, there this Divine Perſon is ſupremely adorable:</hi> As the Divinity every where preſent is every where adorable, and may be ſo adored in the preſence or before any of his Creatures; if ſuch adoration be directed to <hi>him,</hi> not <hi>it,</hi> (as, when I ſee the Sun riſing, I may lawfully fall down on my knees, and bleſs the Omnipotent Creator of it; and ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24, 25.) <hi>may be,</hi> I ſay, but not, <hi>must:</hi> for where there is only ſuch a general preſence of the Divinity; as is in every <hi>time, place,</hi> and <hi>thing;</hi> here our Adoration may and muſt be diſpenſed with, as to ſome times; and places.</p>
            <p>None likewiſe can deny, That the Humanity of our Lord alſo, in a notion abſtractive from the Divinity perſonally united to it, is truly adorable; tho' this with a worſhip not exceeding that due to a Creature.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>4</label>[For the lawfulneſs of Adoration, where ever is ſuch a preſence of the perſon of our Lord, ſee Biſhop <hi>Andrews, Reſp. ad Apol. p.</hi> 195. <hi>Chriſtus ipſe Sacramenti res [ſive] in &amp; cum Sacramento, ſive extra &amp; ſine Sacramento, ubi-ubi eſt, adorandus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Apol. des Eglis. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. c. 10.</note> Thus alſo <hi>Daillé, Apol. des Eglis. Reform. c.</hi> 10. who, in pitching eſpecially on this point, <hi>Adoration of the Euchariſt,</hi> as hindring the Proteſtants longer ſtay in the Roman Communion, hath in this Diſcourſe, and in two Replies to <hi>Chaumont</hi> made afterward in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it, diſcuſſed it more particularly than many others) in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> their adoring the fleſh of Chriſt in the Myſteries.—<hi>The Humanity of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt (ſaith he) <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally united to the Divinity, is by conſequence truly and properly ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi> And again: <hi>They only adored</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in the Sacrament; which is the thing we agree to.</hi> And <hi>ibid. p.</hi> 29. <hi>We do willingly adore</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>who is preſent in the Sacrament, namely by Faith in the heart of the Communicants,</hi> &amp;c. And ſee Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> in his <hi>Roman. Idol. c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 114.—<hi>The Queſtion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, is not whether the perſon of Chriſt is to be worſhipped with Divine worſhip, for that we freely acknowledge. And altho' the humane nature of Christ, of it ſelf, can yield us no ſufficient reaſon for adoration</hi> [he muſt mean, Divine]: <hi>yet being conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as united to the Divine Nature, that cannot hinder, the ſame Divine worſhip being given to his Perſon, which belongs to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature; any more than the Robes of a Prince can take off from the honour due unto him.</hi> Tho' how well that which he ſaith before, <hi>ibid.</hi> §. 2. (as it ſeems againſt worſhipping Chriſt ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed preſent in the Euchariſt, without a ſpecial command to do it)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63863:5"/>conſiſts with what he ſaith here, and with what follows, let him look to it.]</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is affirmed by many Proteſtants,<note place="margin">§. 5. n. 1.</note> eſpecially thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>this Body and Blood of our Lord is really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, not only in virtue, but in ſubſtance in the Euchariſt,</hi> either with the Symbols immediately upon the Conſecration; or at leaſt ſo, as to be received in the Euchariſt, together with the Symbols, by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very worthy Communicant: and that this Body and Blood of our Lord, which is not ſevered from his Perſon, is then to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with ſupreme Adoration.</p>
            <p>[See 1. for a <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> preſence of Chriſt's body in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, (I mean at leaſt to the worthy Receiver, contradiſtinct to a Preſence by <hi>effect</hi> only, Influence, Virtue, Grace, or the Holy Spirit, uniting us to Chriſt's Body in Heaven) Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> of <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> p. 12. <hi>When the word Real</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is denied</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> by Proteſtants, as it was in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time] <hi>the word</hi> Real is <hi>taken for</hi> Natural, [<hi>i. e.</hi> as he explains it p. 5. including not only the nature of the Body, for that is the ſubſtance; but the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and natural manner of its exiſtence: he goes on,] <hi>But the word</hi> ſubſtantialiter <hi>is alſo uſed by Proteſtants in this queſtion, which I ſuppoſe may be the ſame with that which is in the Article of</hi> Trent; Sacramentaliter praeſens Salvator ſubſtantia ſua nobis adeſt; <hi>in</hi> ſubſtance, <hi>but after a Sacramental manner.</hi> See the Confeſſion of <hi>Beza,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants (related by <hi>Hoſp. Hist. Sacram. part. ult.</hi> p. 251..) <hi>Fatemur in coena Domini non modo omnia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti beneficia, ſed ipſam etiam Filii hominis</hi> ſubſtantiam, <hi>ipſam, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam, veram <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arnem &amp; verum illum ſanguinem, quem fudit pro nobis, non ſignificari duntaxat, aut ſymbolice, typice, vel figurate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poni tanquam abſentis memoriam; ſed vere ac certo repraeſentari, exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri, &amp; applicanda oſſerri, adjunctis ſymbolis minime nudis, ſed quae (quod ad Deum ipſum promittentem &amp; offerentem attinet) ſemper rem ipſam vere ac certo</hi> conjunctam <hi>habeant; ſive fidelibus, ſive infidelibus proponantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Beza</hi> Epiſt 68. ſpeaking againſt <hi>Alemannus,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who oppoſed a <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> preſence; <hi>Volunt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ex</hi>-Gallica <hi>Confeſſione</hi> [Art. 36.] <hi>&amp; Liturgia</hi> [Catech. Din. 53.] <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pungi</hi> ſubſtantiae <hi>vocem, idcirco de induſtria paſſim a</hi> Calvino <hi>&amp; a me uſurpatam, ut eorum calumniae occurreremus, qui nos clamitant pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Sacramenti non ipſum Chriſtum, ſed ejus duntaxat dona &amp; ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giam, ponere.</hi> And <hi>Epist.</hi> 5. he argues thus againſt the ſame <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus.</hi>—<hi>Velim igitur te imprimis intueri Christi verba;</hi> Hoc eſt corpus meum, quod pro vobis traditur, <hi>&amp;</hi> Hic eſt ſanguis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63863:6"/>qui pro vobis funditur.—<hi>Age pro his vocibus</hi> Corpus <hi>&amp;</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis, <hi>dicamus, Hoc eſt</hi> efficacia <hi>mortis meae, quae pro vobis tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; Hic eſt</hi> Spiritus <hi>meus qui pro vobis effunditur: Quid ineptius eſt hac oratione? Nam certe verba illa,</hi> Quod pro vobis traditur; <hi>&amp;</hi> Qui pro vobis funditur, <hi>neceſſario huc te adigunt, ut de ipſamet Corporis &amp; Sanguinis</hi> ſubſtantia <hi>hoc intelligere cogaris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See <hi>Hooker, Eccleſ. Pol.</hi> 5. l. 67. §. p. 357. <hi>Wherefore ſhould the world continue ſtill diſtracted and rent with ſo manifold contentions; when there remaineth now no Controverſy, ſaving only about the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject where Christ is?</hi>—<hi>Nor doth any thing reſt doubtful in this, but whether, when the Sacrament is administred, Chriſt be whole with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Man only; or elſe his Body and Blood be alſo externally ſeated in the very conſecrated Elements themſelves?</hi> [But a great Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy ſurely there would be beſide this, if the one party held <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Body <hi>ſubſtantially,</hi> and the other <hi>virtually</hi> preſent.] Again, <hi>p.</hi> 360.—<hi>All three opinions do thus far accord in one,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That theſe holy myſteries, received in due manner, do inſtrumentally both make us par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that body, and blood, which were given for the life of the World; and beſides alſo impart unto us, even in true and real, tho' my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, manner, the very Perſon of our Lord himſelf, whole, perfect, and entire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus alſo Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> Reſp. ad Apol. Bell. 1. cap. p. 11. <hi>Nobis vobiſcum de Objecto convenit, de modo lis omnis eſt.</hi> [But there would be a <hi>lis</hi> concerning the Object, if one affirmed the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the body there, the other only the <hi>virtue,</hi> or efficacy.]</p>
            <p>See Biſhop <hi>Coſins</hi> his late <hi>Hiſtoria Tranſubſtantiationis, tit. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Proteſtantium omnium conſenſus de</hi> reali,<note place="margin">§. 5. n. 2.</note> 
               <hi>id est, vera,</hi> (<hi>ſed non</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nali) <hi>Praeſentia Chriſti in</hi> Euchariſtia <hi>manifeſte constat.</hi> And in proof of this <hi>p.</hi> 10. he quotes <hi>Poinet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> his <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacticon de veritate, natura, atque ſubstantia Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Chriſti in Euchariſtia; Quod</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>non alio conſilio edidit, quam ut fidem &amp; doctrinam Eccleſiae Anglicanae illuſtraret. Et primo oſtendit</hi> Euchariſtiam non ſolum figuram <hi>eſſe Corporis Domini; ſed etiam ipſam veritatem, naturam, atque ſubſtantiam in ſe comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere; idcirco nec has voces</hi> Naturae <hi>&amp;</hi> Subſtantiae <hi>fugiendas eſſe; Veteres enimde hoc Sacramento diſſerentes ita locutos fuiſſe. Secundo quaerit, an voces illae,</hi> Veritas, Natura, <hi>&amp;</hi> Subſtantia, <hi>communi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in hoc myſterio a veteribus intelligebantur; an peculiari &amp; Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis magis accommodata ratione? Neque enim obſervandum eſſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, quibus verbis olim Patres uſi ſunt, ſed quid iſtis ſignificare ac docere voluerint. Et licet diſcrimen ipſe cum Patribus agnoſcat, inter Corpus Chriſti</hi> formam humani corporis naturalem habens, <hi>&amp; quod
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63863:6"/>in Sacramento eſt Corpus</hi> myſticum; <hi>maluit tamen diſcrimen illud</hi> ad modum praeſentiae <hi>&amp;</hi> exhibitionis, <hi>quam ad</hi> ipſam rem, <hi>hoc eſt,</hi> Corpus Chriſti verum <hi>accommodari; cum certiſſimum ſit, non aliud Corpus in Sacramento fidelibus dari, niſi quod a Chriſto pro fidelium ſalute in mortem traditum fuit.</hi> Thus he, juſtifying <hi>Poinet</hi>'s expreſſions ſpeaking in the language of the Fathers. <hi>p.</hi> 43.—<hi>Non dicimus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in hac ſacra Coena nos tantum eſſe participes fructus mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp; paſſionis Chriſti; ſed fundum ipſum cum fructibus, qui ab ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ad nos redeant, conjungimus; aſſerentes cum Apoſtolo,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16. Panem quam frangimus eſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Corporis Chriſti, &amp; Poculum Sanguinis ejus communicationem; <hi>imo in eadem illa ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia, quam accepit in utero Virginis, &amp; quam ſurſum in coelos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vexit; in hoc tantum a Pontiſiciis diſſidentes, quod illi manducationem hanc &amp; conjunctionem, corporaliter fieri credunt; nos non naturali aliqua ratione, aut modo corporali; ſed tamen tam vere, quam ſi na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliter aut corporaliter Chriſto conjungeremur.</hi> [Here I underſtand his <hi>non modo corporali</hi> not to exclude <hi>Corpus Domini,</hi> or <hi>non ratione naturali</hi> to exclude <hi>natura rei,</hi> or the thing it ſelf; but only to ſignify, that the Body is preſent, not after a corporal manner, or with the dimenſions and other common qualities of a Body; which thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Catholicks alſo affirm.]</p>
            <p>He ſeems alſo to grant,<note place="margin">§. 5. n. 3.</note> this ſubſtantial Preſence to be with the Symbols, after Conſecration, on the Table, and before communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating. For <hi>p.</hi> 65. for this he quotes the <hi>Conc. Nicaen. Sublata in altum mente per fidem conſideremus, proponi in ſacra illa menſa Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Dei tollentem peccata mundi.</hi> And p. 43.—<hi>Quoniam</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>res ſignificata nobis offertur &amp; exhibetur tam vere quam ſigna ipſa: ea ratione ſignorum cum Corpore &amp; Sanguine Domini conjunctionem agnoſcimus; &amp; mutata eſſe elementa dicimus in uſum alium ab eo quem prius habuerunt.</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> to be now conjoyned with, and to exhibit to us this Body of our Lord: which conjunction, he ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 45. is made <hi>per omnipotentiam Dei.</hi>] So he ſaith <hi>ibid.</hi>—<hi>Non quaeritur, An Corpus Chriſti a Sacramento ſuo, juxta mandatum ejus inſtituto ac uſurpato, abſit; quod nos Proteſtantes &amp; Reformati nequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam dicimus aut credimus. Nam cum ibi detur &amp; ſumatur, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino oportet ut adſit; licet Sacramento ſuo quaſi contectum ſit, &amp; ibi, ut in ſe eſt, conſpici nequeat.</hi> And p. 125.—<hi>Fieri enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>de Elemento Sacramentum</hi> [which ſurely is done in the Conſecration] <hi>nec conſiſtere Sacramentum ſine Re Sacramenti, firmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tenent.</hi> And this <hi>conjunctio Corporis Chriſti,</hi> p. 35. he affirms to be made in receiving the Sacrament, not only <hi>cum anima, ſed etiam cum corpore noſtro.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63863:7"/>
            <p> Laſtly,<note place="margin">§. 5. n. 4.</note> the <hi>modus</hi> of this true Preſence of the Body of our Lord with the Signs or Symbols in the Sacrament, when as it remains in Heaven till our Lord's ſecond coming, he makes, as others, to be <hi>ineffabilis, imperſcrutabilis, non ratione inquirendus aut indagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</hi> p. 36.—<hi>Nos vero hunc modum</hi> [praeſentiae Chriſti in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtia] <hi>fatemur cum Patribus eſſe ineffabilem, atque imperſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilem, hoc eſt, non ratione inquirendum, aut indagandum; ſed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la fide credendum. Etſi enim videtur incredibile in tanta locorum diſtantia penetrare ad nos</hi> Chriſti <hi>carnem, ut nobis ſit in cibum; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſſe tamen oportet, quantum ſupra ſenſus noſtros emineat Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Sancti virtus, &amp; quam ſtultum ſit ejus immenſitatem modo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro metiri velle. Quod ergo mens noſtra non comprehendit, concipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at fides.</hi> [The like to which <hi>eſſe ineffabilem, &amp; ſupra ſenſus,</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks ſay of the ſame preſence of our Lord in the Euchariſt <hi>in tanta locorum diſtantia,</hi> whilſt alſo at the very ſame time it is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.] And thus <hi>Lanfrank</hi> long ago in his anſwer to <hi>Berengarius,</hi> (who contended that <hi>Chriſti Corpus coelo devocari non poterit,</hi>) quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the words of St. <hi>Andrew</hi> a little before his Paſſion:—<hi>Cum vero in terris carnes ejus ſunt comeſtae, &amp; vere ſanguis ejus ſit bibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus; ipſe tamen uſque in tempora reſtitutionis omnium in coeleſtibus ad dextram Patris integer ſemper perſeverat &amp; vivat. Si quaeris</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>modum quo id fieri poſſit; breviter ad praeſens reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo, Myſterium eſt fidei: credi ſalubriter poteſt, veſtigari utiliter non poteſt.</hi> See alſo the <hi>Gallican</hi> Confeſſion, produced by this Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, <hi>p.</hi> 23. where they ſay, <hi>Christus in coelis manſurus donec ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niat;</hi> and yet <hi>nutriens &amp; vivificans nos Corporis &amp; Sanguinis ſui ſubſtantia,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> in the Sacrament:] that <hi>Hoc myſterium noſtrae cum Chriſto coalitionis tam ſublime eſt, ut omnes noſtros ſenſus, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumque adeo ordinem naturae ſuperat.</hi> In all theſe then doth not the incomprehenſibility and ſupernaturality of this Myſtery lie in this, that the one Body of our Lord ſhould be at once in two places, <hi>viz.</hi> preſent at the ſame time in Heaven, and to us here in the Sacrament? And yet this Biſhop ſeems to find ſome trouble in it, to make any other unexplicable or unintelligible myſtery in the <hi>Catholicks</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, ſave only this. See <hi>p.</hi> 122. For the ceaſing of the ſubſtance of the Elements by God's Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency he allows very feiſible; and then the Adduction of Chriſt's Body (pre-exiſtent) in the place of their ſubſtance, labours under no other difficulty, ſave this, this Body its being at once in two places, here and in Heaven: nor, having twice<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 122. &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 125</note> mentioned ſuch a Sacramental Preſence of our Lord, hath he replied any thing againſt it, but that thus the term of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63863:7"/>rightly applied to ſuch an Adduction; which is a <hi>Logomachy.</hi> But this ſeems the difficulty and incomprehenſibility that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> alſo confeſs in their Sacramental Preſence of our Lord <hi>in tanta loco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſtantia paſcentis nos in Euchariſtia vera Corporis ſui praeſentia &amp; ſubſtantia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, after this Biſhop, with others,<note place="margin">§. 5. n. 5.</note> hath ſo far conformed to the Expreſſions and Language of the Fathers, as to allow an Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial or Subſtantial preſence of Chriſt's Body, it ſeems he finds ſome of theſe Expreſſions alſo ſo far to advance toward a Subſtantial tranſmutation of the Elements, as that he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 113.—<hi>Non abnuimus, nonnulla apud</hi> Chryſoſtomum <hi>alioſque Patres inveniri, quae emphatice, immo vero Hyperbolice de Euchariſtia prolata ſunt: Et quae, niſi dextre capiantur, incautos homines facile in errores ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducent.</hi> And below: <hi>Sanctiſſimi Patres quo haec auditorum animis vehementius &amp; efficacius imprimerent, de Typis, tanquam ſi eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ipſa Antitypa, Oratorum more multa enunciant.</hi> And again, <hi>p.</hi> 117. <hi>Si verba</hi> [i. e. of ſome of the Fathers] <hi>nimis rigide urgeantur abſque intellectu Sacramentali; nihil aliud ex iis colligi poteſt, quam Panem &amp; Vinum proprie &amp; realiter ipſum Christi Corpus &amp; Sanguinem eſſe; quod ne ipſi quidem Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores admittunt.</hi> Where he granting the expreſſions of ſome of the Fathers ſo high as to tranſcend the Aſſertions of Catholicks, or Tranſubſtantiators; whoſe Aſſertions again tranſcend thoſe of Proteſtants in this Myſtery: it ſeems not reaſonable, that he ſhould after this depreſs and extenuate their meanings, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and comply rather with that Opinion that is farther di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from their expreſſions. Neither will the ſame Fathers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in other places, the Elements <hi>Symbols</hi> and <hi>Signs</hi> of Chriſt's Body, (as he pleadeth <hi>p.</hi> 116.) afford him that relief he ſeeks for from it. For ſince the Catholicks, as well as Proteſtants, do firmly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and profeſs an external Symbol, as well as the thing ſignified in the Euchariſt, <hi>viz.</hi> all that is perceived by our ſenſes, and that is viſible, guſtable, or tangible, of the <hi>Elements;</hi> as the Proteſtants contend this Symbol to be not only theſe, but the very Subſtance and nature of the Elements alſo: here it will be found that theſe ſentences of the Fathers do ſuffer much leſs force and torture, if underſtood according to the <hi>Symbol</hi> ſuppoſed by Catholicks, than that by Proteſtants. For example, the Biſhop<note n="*" place="margin">p. 12<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> hath mentioned that paſſage of the ancient Author <hi>de Coena Domini</hi> in S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Works: the words are theſe;—<hi>Panis iſte quem Dominus diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulis porrigebat, non effigie ſed natura mutatus, Omnipotentia Verbi factus eſt caro: &amp; ſicut in perſona Chriſti Humanitas ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parebat,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63863:8"/>&amp; latebat Divinitas; ita Sacramento viſibili ineffabiliter divina ſe effudit eſsentia.</hi> Here, I ſay, if the <hi>Sacramentum viſibile,</hi> and the external Symbol be taken in this Biſhops way, for <hi>ſubſtantia</hi> or <hi>natura panis,</hi> all is extremely forced, and confounded; and ſo he is driven to expound it, that by <hi>mutatio naturae panis</hi> is meant only <hi>mutatio uſus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">p. 120.</note>; the change of which uſe of the Bread alſo ſeems no object of God's Omnipotence. But the Symbol or Sacrament being taken for ſuch as the Catholicks make it, <hi>viz.</hi> for the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Effigies</hi> or Senſibles of the Bread, all is good ſenſe and coherent, and nothing ſtrained: and the <hi>Omnipotentia Verbi</hi> rightly applied to the <hi>mutatio naturae panis:</hi> as God's Omnipotency may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Fathers to be frequently urged, not only in relation to the preſence of our Lord's Body and Blood there, but alſo to the tranſmutation of the Elements there, whilſt the exteriors of them ſtill remain. But now in the laſt place, ſuppoſing the <hi>natura panis</hi> to remain, which the Father ſaith is changed, yet ſo long as theſe Divines maintain according to the Doctrine of the Fathers a ſubſtantial preſence of our Lord's Body in the Euchariſt, and that with the Symbols (as he ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>Sacramento ſuo quaſi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectum</hi>); tho' they will not admit ſuch a Symbol as the Catholicks, and a Tranſubſtantiation of the Elements; yet they muſt (if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with the Fathers) at leaſt confeſs ſome kind of Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation or conjunction of the ſubſtances of Chriſt's Body and of the Elements in the Euchariſt; to which opinion the ſayings of the 0139 0979 V Fathers conſtrained <hi>Luther,</hi> as he often profeſſeth. Mean while if it be asked, why ſuch a Conſubſtantiation is declined by Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks? their anſwer is ready: <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the greateſt <hi>Councils</hi> that have been held ſucceſſively in the Church-Catholick, upon and ſince the agitation of this controverſy, have frequently and conſtantly ſtated and delivered, That the Scriptures, as underſtood and expounded by the Fathers and Church-Tradition, declare a Tranſubſtantiation; in the Judgments of which Councils Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks hold it their Duty to acquieſce. <hi>This of a Subſtantial Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence aſſerted by Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Next,<note place="margin">§. 6. n. 1.</note> for <hi>Adoration</hi> too of this Body, as there preſent either with the Symbols upon their Conſecration, or at leaſt to all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receivers, ſee the ſame Biſhop <hi>Andrews, ib. c.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 195; where to what <hi>Bellarmin</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>Inter novitia &amp; nupera dogmata ponit Adorationem Sacramenti Euchariſtae,</hi> i. e. <hi>adorationem Chriſti Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini in Sacramento, miro, ſed vero modo praeſentis,</hi> he anſwers thus: <hi>Sacramenti ait, id est, Chriſti Domini in Sacramento. Rex autem Chriſtum in Euchariſtia vere praeſentem, vere &amp; adorandum
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63863:8"/>ſtatuit, rem ſcil. Sacramenti; at non Sacramentum.</hi> And—<hi>Nos vero &amp; in myſteriis carnem Chriſti adoramus, cum</hi> Ambroſio; <hi>&amp; non</hi> id [<hi>i. e.</hi> Sacramentum] <hi>ſed</hi> eum, <hi>qui ſuper altare colitur,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> Chriſtum rem Sacramenti.] And is not this <hi>res Sacramenti</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as upon the Altar too with the Symbols there?</p>
            <p>Since him, Biſhop <hi>Bramhal</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rep. to Chalced. 2. c. p. 57.</note> asking, how the Proteſtants could profeſs to agree in all eſſentials of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with the Roman Church, which they held to be an idolatrous Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> in worſhipping the Sacrament as their God? thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies: <hi>The Sacrament is to be adored, ſaid the Council of</hi> Trent: The Sacrament, <hi>i. e. formally the Body and Blood of Chriſt, ſay ſome of your Authors,</hi> [where he quotes <hi>Bellarmin de Sacramento,</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>c.</hi>] <hi>we ſay the ſame.</hi> [So Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal</hi> are agreed about this Adoration of our Lord in the Euchariſt.] The Sacrament, <hi>i. e. the ſpecies of Bread and Wine, ſay others: that we deny, and eſteem it to be idolatrous. Should we charge the whole Church with Idolatry for the Error of a party?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame conceſſion with the ſame diſtinction makes the French-Proteſtant Divine <hi>Daille,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 6. n. 0139 0979 V 3 2.</note> in his ſecond Reply to <hi>Chaumont, p.</hi> 29. <hi>There is a vaſt difference between</hi> to adore the Sacrament, <hi>and 013 to adore</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in the Sacrament, or in the Myſteries.</hi>—<hi>The later of theſe we freely do, ſince we believe him God bleſſed for ever together with the Father.</hi> And afterwards, in anſwer to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: <hi>They ſpeak</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of the Fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt in the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, (of which we do not conteſt the Adoration) and not of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</hi> And again: <hi>They only adored Jeſus Chriſt in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the thing we agree to.</hi> And in his Apology, <hi>Ch</hi>—<hi>p</hi>—he ſaith concerning the Body of Chriſt if in the Sacrament, <hi>That it is evident, that one may, and that one ought to worſhip it: ſeeing that the Body of Chriſt is a ſubject adoreable.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. he grants upon <hi>Adorate ſcabellum,</hi>—<hi>Thatthe faithful caſt down themſelves before the Ark to adore the Lord there, where the Divine Service was particularly joyned to the place where the Ark was.</hi> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Real preſence, §. 13. n. 5.</note>,—<hi>Concerning the action of Adoration, it is a fit addreſs in the day of Solemnity with a</hi> ſurſum corda, <hi>with our hearts lift up to Heaven, where Chriſt ſits (we are ſure) at the right hand of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For,</hi> nemo digne manducat, niſi prius adoraverit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> [which, rightly underſtood, means <hi>illud quod manducat.</hi>] Here the Doctor allows adoring in the the Sacrament Chriſt as in Heaven. But if Chriſt's Body (and ſo himſelf in a ſpecial manner) be ſubſtantial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent in the Euchariſt, here on Earth; why not adore him, not only as in Heaven, but as preſent here? See elſewhere, <hi>Real
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63863:9"/>Preſ.</hi> p. 144. where he ſaith, <hi>We worſhip the fleſh of Chriſt in the Myſteries exhibiting it to our Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See <hi>Spalatenſis de rep. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 7. c. 11. §. 7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">§. 6. n. 3.</note>—<hi>Si ſecundum veritatem qui digne ſumit ſacramenta corporis &amp; ſanguinis Chriſti, ille vere &amp; realiter corpus &amp; ſanguinem Chriſti, in ſe corporaliter, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do tamen quodam ſpirituali, miraculoſo, &amp; imperceptibili, ſumit; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis digne communicans adorare poteſt &amp; debet corpus Chriſti quod reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit.</hi> [Is then the worthy Communicant to worſhip, but not the unworthy; becauſe Chriſt's Body is there preſent to the one, but not to the other?] <hi>Non quod lateat corporaliter in pane, aut ſub pane, aut ſub ſpeciebus &amp; accidentibus panis; ſed quod quando digne ſumitur panis ſacramentalis, tunc etiam ſumitur cum pane Chriſti corpus reale, illi communioni realiter praeſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns.</hi> Thus <hi>Spalatenſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo Biſhop <hi>Forbes, de Euchar.</hi> 2. l. 2. c. 9. §.—<hi>An Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus in uſtia ſit adorandus, Proteſtantes ſaniores non dubitant. In ſumptione enim Euchariſtiae (ut utar verbis Archiepiſcopi</hi> Spalaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis) <hi>adorandus eſt Chriſtus vera latria, ſiquidem corpus ejus vivum, ac glorioſum, miraculo quodam ineffabili digne ſumenti praeſens adeſt; &amp; haec adoratio non pani, non vino, non ſumptioni, non comeſtioni, ſed ipſi Corpori immediate, per ſumptionem Euchariſtiae exhibito, debetur, &amp; perficitur.</hi> [Thus then Proteſtants allow Adoration to Chriſt's Body and Blood, as ſubſtantially preſent in the Euchariſt, if not to the Symbols, yet to the worthy receiver.]</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>7</label> 5ly. Yet further; It is affirmed by another party of Proteſtants, the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> more expreſly, that Chriſt's body and blood are <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> not only to the worthy Communicant, but to the <hi>conſecrated Symbols;</hi> and whilſt ſo preſent, which is during the action of the Lord's Supper, (<hi>i. e.</hi> as I conceive them, from the Conſecration till the end of the Communion) <hi>are to be adored.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[Of which thus <hi>Chemnitius, Exam. Conc. Trid.</hi> part. 2. ſeſſ. 13. c. 5. <hi>Deum &amp; Hominem in Divina &amp; humana natura, in actione Coenae Dominicae vere &amp; ſubſtantialiter praeſentem, in ſpiritu &amp; veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate adorandum, nemo negat; niſi qui cum Sacramentariis vel negat, vel dubitat de praeſentia Chriſti in coena.</hi> Ibid.—<hi>Et quidem hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam etiam ejus naturam, propter unionem cum Divinitate, eſſe ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randam, nemo niſi</hi> Neſtorianus <hi>in dubium vocat.</hi>—<hi>Ita</hi> Jacob <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. Moſes <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. Elias 3 <hi>Reg.</hi> 19. <hi>non habebant ſane peculiare mandatum, ut in illis locis Deum adorarent: ſed quia habebant generale mandatum ut Deum ubique adorarent, &amp; certi erant Deum ſub exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; viſibilibus illis ſymbolis vere adeſſe, &amp; peculiari modo gratiae ſe ibi patefacere; certe Deum ipſum, quem ibi preſentem eſſe credebant, adorabant. Nec vero Deum illi procul in coelo Empyraeo a ſe remotum
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63863:9"/>&amp; abſentem, ſed vere praeſentem, &amp; quidem peculiari modo gratiae praeſentem, adorarunt.</hi>—Thus he. Nor do I know, that the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts</hi> have at any time accuſed their brethren the <hi>Lutherans</hi> of Idolatry in ſuch a practice. I find alſo Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> in the like manner clearly maintaining, 1. A preſence of Chriſt's Body with the ſymbols, immediately upon Conſecration: and, 2. An Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion due to it. See the <hi>former,</hi> in <hi>Epilog. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. and, 3. where <hi>p.</hi> 17. <hi>I have ſaid enough</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to evidence the myſtical and ſpiritual preſence of the fleſh and blood of Chriſt in the Elements, as the Sacrament of the ſame, before any Man can ſuppoſe that ſpiritual preſence of them to the ſoul, which the eating and drinking Chriſt's fleſh and blood ſpiritually by living Faith importeth.</hi> And ſee the <hi>latter,</hi> ib. c. 30. p. 350.—<hi>I ſuppoſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Body and Blood of Chriſt may be adored where-ever they are; and muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored by a good Chriſtian, where the cuſtom of the Church, which a Chriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is obliged to communicate with, requires it.</hi>—<hi>This honour</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> of worſhipping the Body and Blood of Chriſt] <hi>being the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an affirmative precept, (which, according to the received rule, tyes always; tho' it cannot tye a Man to do the duty always, becauſe he then ſhould do nothing elſe:) what remains but a juſt occaſion to make it requiſite, and preſently to take hold and oblige? And is not the preſence thereof in the Sacrament of the Euchariſt a juſt</hi> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>preſently to expreſs by the bodily act of Adoration, that inward honour, which we always carry toward our Lord Chriſt as God?</hi>—Again p. 351. <hi>Not to balk that freedom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which hath carried me to publiſh all this: I do believe that it was ſo practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and done</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> our Lord Chriſt really worſhipped in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt] <hi>in the ancient Church, and in the ſymbols before receiving; which I maintain from the beginning to have been the true Church of Chriſt, obliging all to conform to it in all things within the power of it. I know the conſequence to be this, That there is no juſt cauſe why it ſhould not be done at preſent, but that cauſe which juſtifies the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of ſome part of the Church without the whole: which, were it taken away, that it</hi> [this adoration] <hi>might be done again, and ought not to be, of it ſelf alone, any cauſe of Diſtance</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> between the Churches of Chriſt.]</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is granted by <hi>Daille</hi> in his <hi>Apology,</hi> c. 11. and in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it againſt <hi>Chaumont,</hi> 1. That altho' the Reformed of his party, do not believe the preſence of Chriſt's body in the Signs, yet they <hi>eſteem not the belief of it ſo criminal, that it obligeth them to break off communion with all thoſe that hold it.</hi> So that, had the Roman Church no other error, ſave this, they freely confeſs, it had given
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63863:10"/>them no ſufficient cauſe of ſeparating from it: <hi>as</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in this, that we tolerate and bear with it in the</hi> Lutherans. And again,<note n="*" place="margin">Reply to <hi>Chaumont,</hi> p. 63.</note> for the adoration of this Body as ſo preſent with the ſigns, (when indeed it is not ſo,) he ſaith,—<hi>That it is only vain and unprofitable, and that, as one may ſay, falls to nothing; being deceived not in this, that it makes its addreſſes to an object not adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but in this only, that miſtaking it, it ſeeks it, and thinks to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it there where it is not.</hi> And <hi>c.</hi> 12. he alſo freely confeſſeth, <hi>That had the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>only obliged them to worſhip</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt <hi>in the Sacrament, and not uſed this expreſſion, that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of</hi> Latria <hi>ought to be rendred to the Holy Sacrament:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Conc. <hi>Trid.</hi> ſeſſ. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſhe had not obliged them by this to adore any Creature.</hi> Thus he, as it were conſtrained thereto by the <hi>Lutherans</hi> Proteſtants Opinion and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, for his retaining their Communion, and freeing them from Idolatry. 2. It is granted alſo, <hi>Apol.</hi> c. 11.—That when our Lord was on Earth, a Diſciple's giving divine honours, upon mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, to another perſon much reſembling him, would be no Idolatry. So, ſuppoſing the Conſecrated Hoſt were truly ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, granted, that ſhould any one ſee one on the Altar, that hapned not to be Conſecrated, and Worſhip it, neither would ſuch a perſon be guilty of Idolatry. So he pronounces him blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that ſhould give the Honour and Service due to his true Prince to a Subject, whom, very like, he took for his Prince. Yet that a <hi>Manichean</hi> worſhipping the Sun, miſtaken to be the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſt, (ſee S. <hi>Auſtin contra Fauſtum</hi> l. 12. c. 22. l. 20. c. 9.) for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or (to repreſent the opinion more refined) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping with divine honours not the Sun, but only Chriſt in the Sun, he could not in this be excuſed from Idolatry. And, that that which diſtinguiſhes theſe caſes, and renders them ſo different, is, not a good intention to worſhip only him that is truly God, or Chriſt; nor the opinion and belief Men have, that the Object they worſhip is truly ſuch; for this good intention (as he in that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and other Reformed Writers, and among others Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> copiouſly preſs) is common to the worſt of Idolaters, as to the reſt: but the error or ignorance of the Judgment, from which flows this miſtaking practice; as that is perverſly <hi>affected</hi> and culpable, or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> and excuſable. Of which thus he, <hi>Ibid.</hi>—<hi>I maintain, that ignorance excuſeth here when it is involuntary; when the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> [I add, or the preſence of it] <hi>we miſtake in, is ſo concealed, that whatever deſire we have, or pains we take, to find out the truth, it is not poſſible for us to diſcover it.</hi>—<hi>But there, where the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Object</hi> [or of its preſence] <hi>proceeds not from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63863:10"/>or difficulty of the thing, but from the malice or negligence of the perſon; this is ſo far from excuſing, that it aggravates our fault.</hi> Thus he excuſes one that ſhould have adored a perſon much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling our Lord, or an unconſecrated Hoſt,—<hi>becauſe no paſſion or negligence of his cauſed ſuch a miſtake:</hi>—<hi>but not thoſe who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Sun for</hi> Chriſt, [<hi>or</hi> Chriſt in the Sun;]—<hi>becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the ignorance of ſuch people is viſibly affected and volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ariſing from their fault only, and not from the obſcurity of the things they are ignorant in.</hi> Nor ſo <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks in their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Sacrament for Chriſt; <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the error proceeds entirely from their paſſion, and not any thing from abroad.</hi> [Thus he, clearing ſuch actions from Idolatry, where the error of the judgment is no way perverſe, voluntary, and culpable.]</p>
            <p>Having hitherto ſhewed you ſeveral Conceſſions of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and having urged none here from any of them, but ſuch as I think all will, or in reaſon ought, to admit; next I proceed to examine, what it is that in this matter <hi>Catholicks</hi> do maintain.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>9</label> 1. And firſt, <hi>Catholicks</hi> affirm in the Euchariſt, after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, a <hi>ſign</hi> or ſymbol to remain ſtill diſtinct;<note place="margin">Aſſertione.</note> and having a diverſe exiſtence from that of the <hi>thing ſignified,</hi> or from <hi>Chriſt's Body</hi> contained in, or under it. [See <hi>Conc. Trident. ſeſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Hoc eſſe commune Euchariſtiae cum aliis Sacramentis, ut ſit ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum rei ſacrae, &amp; viſibilis forma inviſibilis gratiae.</hi> By which <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma viſibilis</hi> (as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> expounds it, <hi>de Euchariſt.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi>) is meant the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the Elements, not the Body of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>—So <hi>Bellarmin, Euchar.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>c. Etiam post conſecrationem ſpecies pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; vini ſunt ſigna corporis &amp; ſanguinis</hi> Chriſti <hi>ibi revera ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtentium.</hi>—And 3. l. 22. c. <hi>Accidentia remanent; quia ſi etiam accidentia abeſſent, nullum eſset in Eucharistia ſignum ſenſibile; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde nullum eſſet Sacramentum.</hi> So <hi>Eſtius</hi> in 4. ſent. 1. diſt. 3. §. <hi>Euchariſtia conſtat ex pane, tanquam materia quadam partim tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeunte, partim remanente; tranſeunte quidem ſecundum ſubſtantiam; remanente vero ſecundum accidentia, in quibus tota ſubſtantiae vis &amp; operatio nihilominus perſeverat.</hi> Hence they allow of that expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 34. <hi>c.</hi> where he ſaith,—<hi>Euchariſtiam ex duabus rebus, terrena &amp; coeleſti, compoſitam eſſe.</hi> And of S. <hi>Gregory, dial.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 58. <hi>c. In hoc myſterio ſumma imis ſociari: terrena coeleſtibus jungi: unum ex viſibilibus ac inviſibilibus fieri.</hi>] So that tho' theſe ſymbols and Chriſt's Body may be ſaid to make <hi>unum aggregatum;</hi> yet, if this be only the <hi>ſpecies</hi> or accidents of the Bread and Wine that remains, theſe cannot be ſaid to have any inherence in this Body of Chriſt, (tho' it is true on the other ſide that, being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63863:11"/>only, they cannot be ſaid to make a diſtinct <hi>ſuppoſitum</hi> from it;) or, if a ſubſtance remain, this cannot be ſaid to have any hypoſtatical union (or to make one <hi>ſuppoſitum</hi>) with our Lord's Divinity or Humanity, as our Lord's Humanity hath ſuch an union with his Divinity. From which it is obſerved by Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> (<hi>Real Preſence,</hi> p. 336.) That therefore ſtill there is the leſs reaſon for <hi>Romaniſts</hi> to give any Divine worſhip (as he ſaith they do) to the ſymbols. Far therefore are Catholicks from granting (what a late Author<note n="*" place="margin">Stilligfl. Rom. Idol. p. 128.</note> pretends they do, but that which he alledgeth no way ſhews it) as great an hypoſtatical union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and the Sacrament, as between the Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>10</label> This external ſign or ſymbol they alſo affirm to be <hi>all that</hi> of the Bread and Wine that is <hi>perceived</hi> by any <hi>ſenſe.</hi> And tho' after ſuch Conſecration the ſubſtance of the Bread and Wine is denied to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main yet is <hi>ſubſtance</hi> here taken in ſuch a ſenſe, as that neither the hardneſs nor ſoftneſs, nor the frangibility, nor the ſavour, nor the odour, nor the nutritive virtue of the Bread, nor nothing viſible, nor tangible, or otherwiſe perceptible by any ſenſe, are involved in it. Of which ſigns alſo they predicate many things, which they will by no means allow to be properly ſaid of, or at leaſt to be received in, or effected by, or upon <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Body, now immortal and utterly impaſſible. So <hi>ſapere, digeri, nutrire, confortare, corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliter;</hi> and again, <hi>frangi dentibus, comburi, rodi a brutis animali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> and whatever other things may be named (excepting only thoſe attributes, which in general are neceſſary to indicate the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Body to us with the <hi>ſpecies</hi> whilſt <hi>integrae;</hi> as the local poſitions, <hi>elevari, recondi, ore recipi,</hi> &amp;c.) they apply to theſe ſymbols that remain; not to <hi>Christ</hi>'s Body which is indiviſibly there.—<hi>Chriſtus vere in ſacramento exiſtens nullo modo laedi poteſt; non cadit in terram,</hi> [id enim proprie cadit <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> quod cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraliter movetur; <hi>ſo alſo,</hi> anima non cadit,] <hi>non teritur, non roditur, non putreſcit, non crematur: illa enim</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellarmin</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">De Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. 3. l. 10. c.</note>) <hi>in ſpeciebus iſtis recipiuntur, ſed Chriſtum non afficiunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>11</label> 2. Concerning Adoration of the Sacrament, they affirm the word <hi>Sacrament, not to be taken always in the ſame ſenſe;</hi> but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be uſed to ſignify only the <hi>external ſigns</hi> or ſymbols; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times only the <hi>res Sacramenti,</hi> or the thing contained under them, which is the much more principal part thereof. And, as <hi>Proteſtants</hi> much preſs, ſo <hi>Catholicks</hi> willingly acknowledge, a great difference between theſe two, the worſhipping of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> as this word is taken for the ſymbols, and the worſhipping of <hi>Christ</hi>'s <hi>Body</hi> in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63863:11"/>the Sacrament. Now as the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> is taken for the <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols,</hi> they acknowledge a certain inferior cult and veneration due thereto, as to other holy things, the holy Chalices, the holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, the holy Croſs, <hi>&amp;c. of which Veneration much hath been ſpoken in the Diſcourſe of</hi> Images, §. 42. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they acknowledge no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme or divine Adoration due to the Sacrament, as taken in this ſenſe for the Symbols; but only to our Lord's Body and Blood, and ſo to our Lord himſelf as preſent in this Sacrament, or with theſe Symbols. [So that be theſe Symbols of what latitude you will, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther larger, as the <hi>Lutheran</hi> believes; or ſtraiter, as the <hi>Catholicks</hi> ſay they are; or be they not only theſe, but the ſubſtance of bread alſo under them, as <hi>Catholicks</hi> believe it is not: yet neither thoſe <hi>ſpecies,</hi> nor this <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> have any divine Adoration given or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged due to them at all; no more than this ſubſtance of bread, believed there by the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> yet hath from them any ſuch Adoration given to it.]</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>12</label>[That Catholicks thus by Adoration of the Sacrament with <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria</hi> only underſtand that of the <hi>res Sacramenti,</hi> the Adoration of Chriſt's Body and Blood in the Sacrament, ſee <hi>Conc. Trid. ſeſs.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>Omnes Chriſti fideles, pro more in Catholica Eccleſia ſemper recepto, latriae cultum, qui vero Deo debetur, huic ſanctiſſimo Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento in veneratione exhibeant. Neque enim ideo minus eſt ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum, quod fuerit a Chriſto Domino, ut ſumatur, inſtitutum; nam illum eundem Deum praeſentem in eo adeſſe credimus, quem Pater aeternus introducens in orbem terrarum dicit,</hi> Et adorent eum omnes Angeli Dei: <hi>quem Magi procidentes adoraverunt.</hi> Where, tho' the Council uſeth the expreſſion of exhibiting <hi>latriae cultum Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento;</hi> yet that this <hi>cultus latriae</hi> is not applied to the Sacrament, as it implies the Sign or Symbol, but only the thing ſignified, both the words joined to it, <hi>qui vero Deo debetur,</hi> (which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Council maintains that to be God they gave this <hi>cultus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae</hi> to) and the explication annexed, <hi>Nam illum eundem Deum,</hi> &amp;c. may ſufficiently convince to any not obſtinately oppoſite. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do thoſe words interpoſed,—<hi>Neque enim ideo [Sacramentum] minus eſt adorandum, quod fuerit a Chriſto Domino, ut ſumatur, inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> any way croſs ſuch a ſenſe, as a late Author<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet, Rom. Idol.</hi> c. 2. §. 2. p. 117.</note> too confidently preſſeth, ſaying,—<hi>That by</hi> Sacrament <hi>here the Council muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Elements or Accidents as the immediate term of that divine worſhip, or elſe the latter words</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> quod fuerit a Domino inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ut ſumatur] <hi>ſignify nothing at all. For what</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was that, which was inſtituted by the Lord as a Sacrament? was it not the external and viſible Signs, or Elements? why do they urge,</hi> That
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63863:12"/>the Sacrament ought not the leſs to be adored, becauſe it was to be taken, <hi>but to take of the common objection,</hi> That we ought not to give divine worſhip to that which we eat? <hi>And what can this have reſpect to, but the Elements?</hi> Thus argues he. When as he might know, that the Fathers of <hi>Trent,</hi> who ſaid this, do hold, the chief thing inſtituted and exhibited in the Sacrament to be, not the Elements, but Chriſt's Body; and <hi>ipſum corpus Domini</hi> to be alſo orally both taken and eaten, (tho' not <hi>modo naturali carnis</hi> or <hi>corporis</hi>) as well as the Elements, according to our Lord's expreſs words, <hi>Accipite, Manducate, Hoc eſt Corpus meum,</hi> [i. e. <hi>quod mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis:</hi>] and when-as he might know alſo, that the occaſion of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this clauſe was in oppoſition to a party of <hi>Luther</hi>'s followers, who, granting Chriſt's Body preſent with the Symbols, and yet denying Adoration, ſaid for it, that our Lord's Body [not the <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol</hi>] was preſent there, <hi>non ut adoretur, ſed ut ſumatur.</hi> And <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo ſaith ſome ſuch thing, <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> l. 4. c. 17. §. 35. urging, there was no ſuch mandate for Adoration, <hi>i. e.</hi> of Chriſt's Body, of which he was formerly ſpeaking; but that our Lord commanded only, <hi>accipite, manducate, bibite,—quo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>accipi</hi> [or <hi>ſumi,</hi> if you will] <hi>Sacramentum, non adorari jubet:</hi> meaning <hi>Sacramentum</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>Corpus Domini;</hi> elſe he ſaid nothing to the purpoſe of his former Diſcourſe. And it may be conſider'd here alſo, that not only the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> but no Schoolman at all (ſome of which are thought uncautious in their expreſſions about Adoration of Images, and conſequently of the holy Symbols in the Euchariſt; nor is any Catholick accountable for them) takes the boldneſs to give <hi>cultus latriae (qui vero Deo debetur,</hi> as the Council ſaith here) to the Elements, without annexing ſome qualification of a <hi>coadoratio, per accidens, improprie, ſicut veſtes Regis adorantur cum Rege,</hi> or <hi>ut Rex veſtitus adoratur,</hi> yet without our mental notion at ſuch a time ſtripping him of his Garments. Therefore neither can the Council here be rationally preſumed to ſpeak of the Symbols, when it uſeth no ſuch qualifications.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>13</label> But, to put this matter out of all doubt, the Definition of this Council in the 6th. <hi>Canon</hi> (more than which is not required to be profeſſed by any Son of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) is this:—<hi>Si quis dixerit in ſancto Euchariſtae Sacramento Chriſtum unigenitum Dei Filium non eſſe cultu latriae etiam externo adorandum,—&amp; ejus Adoratores eſſe Idololatras, Anathema ſit.</hi> Concerning which, and ſome other paſſages in this Council, in comparing the <hi>Chapters</hi> with the <hi>Canons, Franciſcus a ſancta Clara, Enchiridion of Faith Dial.</hi> 3. §. 18. judiciouſly obſerves,—<hi>That altho' Catholick faith,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63863:12"/>as to the ſubſtance, is declared in the Chapters,</hi> (as indeed it is,) <hi>yet according to this we are obliged only</hi> ſub anathemate <hi>to that form of expreſſion which is defined in the</hi> Canons. 1. <hi>Becauſe the</hi> Chapters <hi>are not framed in the ſtile of Conciliary Definitions, with</hi> Anathema <hi>'s, and the like.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe the</hi> Canons (where the very form is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exact) <hi>ſometimes differ from the manner of expreſſion in the</hi> Chapters, <hi>in order to the ſame matter: As</hi> ſeſſ. 6. <hi>of</hi> Juſtification; Canon 11. <hi>and</hi> Chapter 7. <hi>alſo</hi> ſeſſ. 13. <hi>of the</hi> Sacrament of the Euchariſt; Canon 6. Chapter 5. <hi>and elſewhere: yet</hi> ſub anathemate <hi>all muſt ſtand to the</hi> Canons; <hi>and therefore muſt expound the</hi> Chapters <hi>by them.</hi> See more in the Author.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soave</hi> alſo, <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 343. in his cenſure of this 13th. Seſſion, tho' he ſaith magiſterially enough in oppoſition to a Council,—<hi>That the manner of ſpeech uſed in the</hi> 5th. <hi>point of Doctrine, ſaying,</hi> That divine worſhip was due to the Sacrament, <hi>was noted alſo for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper; ſince it is certain, that the thing ſignifyed or contained is not meant by the</hi> Sacrament, <hi>but the thing ſignifying or containing.</hi> [But what Catholick will grant him this, that <hi>Sacrament</hi> includes not both; or, of the two, not more principally the thing contained in, or joined with the Symbols?] Yet he obſerves,—<hi>That it was well corrected in the</hi> 6th. Canon, <hi>which ſaid,</hi> That the Son of God ought to be worſhipped in the Sacrament. See the ſame obſerved alſo by <hi>Grotius</hi> in <hi>Apolog. Rivet Diſcuſſ.</hi> p. 79. where alſo he notes <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s forequoted paſſage: <hi>That the Controverſy between</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks <hi>and</hi> Lutherans <hi>in their ſaying,</hi> The Sacrament, or Chriſt in the Sacrament, was to be worſhipped, <hi>was only</hi> in modo loquendi: To which nothing is replied by <hi>Rivet in Dialyſi Diſcaſſionis,</hi> but the matter there, as alſo in his <hi>Apologetic,</hi> paſſed over in ſilence. Add to <hi>Grotius</hi> what Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> diſcourſeth in defence of the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>worſhipping the Sacrament, Epilog.</hi> 3. l. 30. c. p. 352. <hi>I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it is not (neceſſarily) the ſame thing to worſhip</hi> Chriſt <hi>in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Euchariſt, as to worſhip the</hi> Sacrament <hi>of the Euchariſt. Yet in that ſenſe, which reaſon of it ſelf juſtifies, it is. For the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Euchariſt, by reaſon of the nature thereof, is neither the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> ſpecies, <hi>nor the inviſible Grace of Chriſt's body and blood; but the union of both by virtue of the promiſe; in regard whereof—both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to that which we call the Sacrament of the Euchariſt,—by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which the Institution thereof containeth. If this be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood,</hi> then <hi>to worſhip the</hi> Sacrament <hi>of the Eucharist, is to worſhip Christ in the Sacrament of the Eucharist.</hi> Thus he.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>14</label> This in vindication of the Council. And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> explains himſelf in the ſame manner as the Council, in his Apology to King
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63863:13"/>James, Inter nupera dogmata ponit [Rex] <hi>adorationem Sacramenti Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtiae,</hi> i. e. [as Catholicks underſtand and explain it] <hi>adorationem Chriſti Domini miro, ſed vero, modo praeſentis.</hi> To which Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> replies:—<hi>Quis ei hoc dederit?</hi> Sacramento <hi>i. e.</hi> Chriſti <hi>in Sacramento. Imo Christus ipſe Sacramenti res in Sacramento adorandus est. Rex autem Christum in Eucharistia vere praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, vere &amp; adorandum statuit.</hi> [Thus far then the King, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and Cardinal are agreed] Again, <hi>de Eucharistia</hi> l. 4. c. 29.—<hi>Quicquid ſit de modo loquendi, status Quaestionis non eſt, niſi,</hi> An Chriſtus in Euchariſtia ſit adorandus cultu latriae? And, as it were to avoid offence, when he comes to treat on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>de Euchar.</hi> 4. <hi>l. c.</hi> 29. he prefixeth the Title to it, not <hi>De adoratione,</hi> but <hi>De veneratione hujus Sacramenti:</hi> And in it ſaith that—<hi>Nullus Catholicus eſt qui doceat, Ipſa ſymbola externa per ſe &amp; proprie eſſe</hi> adoranda <hi>cultu latriae, ſed ſolum</hi> veneranda <hi>cultu quodam minore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this Doctrine of Catholicks Biſhop <hi>Forbes</hi> gives this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.9. §. <hi>In Euchariſtia mente diſcernendum eſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum a viſibili ſigno docent</hi> Romanenſes; <hi>&amp; Chriſtum quidem ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum eſſe non tamen Sacramentum: quia ſpecies illae ſunt res creatae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>neque ſatis eſt</hi> [i. e. to give them divine worſhip] <hi>quod Chriſtus ſub illis ſit: quia etiam Deus eſt in Anima tanquam in Templo ſuo; &amp; tamen adoratur Deus, non Anima; ut ait</hi> Suares 3. Tom. 79. quaeſt. 8. art. diſp. 65. §. 1. And ſo <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> l. 7. c. 11. n. 7. <hi>Nam neque noſtri</hi> [i. e. Catholicks] <hi>dicunt ſpecies panis &amp; vini, hoc eſt, accidentia illa eſſe adoranda: ſed dicunt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chriſti verum &amp; reale, quod ſub illis ſpeciebus latet, debere ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari.</hi> When then the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; ſpeaking of ſupreme Adoration, explains her language of <hi>adoring the Sacrament,</hi> to mean only adoring Chriſt's Body, and ſo Chriſt as preſent there; and not adoring any other thing whatever (ſubſtance, or accident) that is preſent there, or that is alſo included in the word <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> that accuſation, which her uſing ſuch language of <hi>adoring the Sacrament</hi> can ſeemingly expoſe her to, is at the moſt, not of an <hi>error,</hi> but an improper expreſſion. But the propriety of language dutiful Sons ought to learn from, not teach, their Mother; who alſo ſpeaks that which hath deſcended to her from former times. Neither will it follow from Catholicks uſing the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> preciſely in this ſenſe, excluſively to any other matter ſave Chriſt's Body, that therefore one may uſe the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly for Chriſt's Body, in what reſpect ſoever we ſpeak of it; and, as well or as properly ſay, that the Sacrament, meaning Chriſt's
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63863:13"/>Body, is in the Heavens at God's right hand, or was on the Croſs, or the like. For tho' <hi>[Sacrament]</hi> thus applied involves no other ſubject or thing at all but Chriſt's Body; yet it <hi>connotes,</hi> beſides it, the place or manner of its preſence; ſignifying this Body only as preſent in the Myſteries; not as a term adequate to, and convertible with it, being in whatever time and place.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>15</label> I think theſe Teſtimonies produced both out of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and other <hi>Catholick</hi> Authors, and alſo out of <hi>Protestants</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing ſo much of them, do ſhow ſufficiently the great extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy of thoſe <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Authors who tell their Readers, that the ſtate of this controverſy is not, Whether <hi>Christ's Body,</hi> and ſo Chriſt in the Sacrament be adorable with ſupreme Honours? but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and then by <hi>Sacrament</hi> are pleaſed to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>Symbols?</hi> and then, to confute the Doctrine of <hi>Rome,</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, that no <hi>Creature,</hi> as the Symbols are, is capable of Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. <hi>The ſtate of the Controverſy</hi> (ſaith a late Writer of theirs<note n="*" place="margin">Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet Rom. Idol p. 117.</note>.) <hi>is, Whether proper Divine Worſhip in the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Euchariſt may be given to the Elements on the account of a Corporal Preſence of Chriſt under them?</hi> And againſt it he affirms,—<hi>That ſuppoſing the divine Nature preſent in any thing gives no ground upon that account to give the ſame worſhip to the thing wherein he is preſent, as I do to Chriſt himſelf.</hi> So Biſhop <hi>Andrews, Rex Chriſtum in Euchariſtia vere adorandum ſtatuit,—at non Sacramentum, terrenam ſcilicet partem.</hi> And—<hi>Nos in myſteriis carnem Chriſti adoramus, Sacramentum</hi> [i. e. the Symbols] <hi>nulli adoramus.</hi> So Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> (Real Preſence p. 335.) <hi>The Commandement to Worſhip God alone is ſo expreſs; the diſtance between God and Bread dedicated to the ſervice is ſo vaſt,—that, if it had been intended that we ſhould have Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the H. Sacrament, the H. Scriptures would have called it God, or</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. And <hi>Diſſwaſive</hi> §. 5. p. 76. he affirms the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to give Divine Honour to the Symbols or Elements, and ſo to a Creature the due and incommunicable propriety of God. So they vainly alſo undertake to ſhew, that the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church did not terminate their Adoration upon the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; that the Fathers, when they ſpeak of worſhip, ſpeak of worſhipping the Fleſh of Chriſt in the Myſteries, or Symbols; not of worſhipping the Myſteries or Symbols. Theſe, I ſay, are great extravagances: whilſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Church owns or impoſes no ſuch Doctrine of Divine Adoration due to the Elements, and the true Controverſy on their ſide is only this; 1. Whether the <hi>Body and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> preſcinding from whatever Symbol is or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63863:14"/>may be there, is <hi>adoreable,</hi> as being preſent in the Sacrament with theſe ſymbols? (This is affirmed by <hi>Catholicks:</hi> more than this needs not be ſo;) And, 2. Whether the <hi>Adoration of Chriſt's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and ſo of Chriſt as preſent, if it ſhould not be ſo, <hi>will amount to Idolatry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>16</label> If we here make a further enquiry into the Schoolmen concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Adoration or Veneration due to the Symbols, they ſtate the ſame toward them as toward Images, the ſacred Utenſils, the H. name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and other Holy things. <hi>Omnes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Vaſquez, in</hi> 3. <hi>Thom. tom.</hi> 1. <hi>diſp.</hi> 108. <hi>c.</hi> 12.) <hi>eodem modo de ſpeciebus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenti, quo de Imaginibus, philoſophari debent.</hi> And then of Images we know the Definition of the <hi>Second</hi> Council of <hi>Nice</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to by <hi>Trent—non latria.</hi> And for what they ſay of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges I refer you to the preceding Diſcourſe on them, §. 42, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is true, that ſome of the later Schoolmen (to defend the expreſſions of ſome of the former) have endeavoured to ſhow how a latrical, qualified, ſecondary co-adoration may <hi>improprie</hi> or <hi>per accidens</hi> be ſaid to be given to the ſymbols alſo, as ſacramentally joyned with our Lord's Body, and as this body is as it were veſted with them; ſuch as, ſay they, when Chriſt was adored here on Earth, was given alſo to his Garments, <hi>i. e.</hi> without making in the act of worſhip a mental ſeparation of his Perſon from his Cloths; as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> explains it, <hi>de Euchar. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 29.—<hi>Neque enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>jubebant Chriſtum veſtibus nudari antequam adorarent; aut animo &amp; cogitatione ſeparabant a veſtibus cum adorarent; ſed ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter Chriſtum, ut tunc ſe habebat, adorabant: tametſi ratio ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi non erant veſtes, imo nec ipſa Humanitas, ſed ſola Divi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itas.</hi> Or do allow the giving of the external ſign of <hi>Latria</hi> to them: as Bowing to, Kiſſing, Embracing them; but this without any the leaſt internal act of <hi>latria,</hi> or any other honour or ſubmiſſion directed to them, which ſuch inanimate things are uncapable of; as <hi>Vaſquez</hi> explains it; who is ſo prodigal of this external ſign of honour, after he hath ſtript it of any internal <hi>latria,</hi> or other worſhip whatever that may accompany it; that he allows this external ſign not only to all Holy things, but to any Creature whatever, (in our inward adoration mean-while only of God,) upon the general relation they have to him. But indeed ſuch an abſtraction of the external ſign, from an internal honour or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect (as other Catholicks cenſure his opinion) makes theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward geſtures, without any mental intention attending them as to ſuch object, like thoſe of a Puppet or Engine, utterly inſignificant: and ſo <hi>Vaſquez,</hi> inſtead of communicating the <hi>latria</hi> to Images,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63863:14"/>to the Symbols, to other Holy things, ſeems, in the judgment of others, to allow them no honour or veneration at all; and ſo, in ſeeming to ſay too much, to ſay too little; which hath been more largely diſcourſed before, <hi>Of Images</hi> §. 42. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And a late Author<note n="*" place="margin">Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet Rom. Idol. p. 129.</note> might have done well, in mentioning this Author's Opinion, to have given alſo a true relation of it, affirming only an external ſign of honour given to the creature void of any internal the leaſt reſpect to them; <hi>Ita ut tota mentis intentio in Exemplar, non in Imaginem</hi> [or, Deum, non Creaturam.] <hi>feratur:</hi> which would eaſily have taken away all that malignity he faſtens upon it. This for <hi>Vaſquez.</hi> And as for <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s adoration <hi>improprie</hi> and <hi>per accidens,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Forbes</hi> tells us <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. §. 11. <hi>Sententia ista</hi> Bellarmini <hi>plurimis Doctoribus Romanenſibus diſplicet.</hi> And <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> himſelf, as appears by the former citations, waving theſe School diſputes, tells us,—<hi>Status Quaestionis non est niſi,</hi> An Chriſtus in Euchariſtia ſit adorandus? <hi>i. e.</hi> no more is defined, decided, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on Chriſtians faith by the Church, than this: nor more needs be deſputed with, or maintained againſt, Proteſtants, than this. [This in the 2<hi>d.</hi> place from §. 11. Of Catholicks profeſſing their Adoration with divine worſhip of Chriſt, only preſent in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with the Symbols, not of the Symbols; or, not, of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, if taken for the Symbols.]</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>17</label> 3<hi>ly.</hi> Therefore alſo Catholicks <hi>ground their Adoration</hi> (a thing Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> much inſiſts upon in his Reply to King <hi>James</hi>) <hi>not on Tranſubstantiation,</hi> (tho' both Tranſubſtantiation and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation involve it; ſo that, either of theſe maintained, Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration neceſſarily follows) as if, Tranſubſtantiation defeated, Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is ſo too; <hi>but on a Real Preſence</hi> with the Symbols; which in general is agreed on by the <hi>Lutheran</hi> together with them. Which Adoration they affirm due, with all the ſame circumſtances where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is now performed, tho' Chriſt's Body were preſent with the Symbols, neither as under the accidents of Bread, as they ſay; nor under the ſubſtance of Bread, as the <hi>Lutheran</hi> ſaith; but, tho' after ſome other unknown manner, diſtinct from both: and if they were convinced of the error of Tranſubſtantiation, and of the truth of the preſence of the ſubſtance of the Bread unchanged; yet as long as not confuted in the point of <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> they would never the leſs for this continue to adore the ſelf ſame Object, as now; in the ſelf ſame place, namely, the Body of Chriſt ſtill preſent there with the Symbols, and therefore there adorable; tho' preſent after another manner than they imagined. See the argument of <hi>Barneſius</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Writer <hi>apud Forbeſ.</hi> l. 2. c. 2. §. 12.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63863:15"/>
               <hi>Corpus. Chriſti eſt cum pane vel permanente, vel tranſeunte, uno vel alio modo, &amp; per conſequens non eſt idololatria adorare Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ibi in Euchariſtia realiter praeſentem.</hi> See in <hi>Conc. Trid.</hi> 13. §. <hi>c.</hi> 5. the reaſon immediately following the requiring of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,—<hi>Nam illum eundem Deum praeſentem in eo</hi> [i.e. Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to] <hi>adeſſe credimus, quem Pater introducens in orbem terrarum dicit,</hi> Et adorent eum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore the <hi>Roman</hi> Church enjoyns theſe three: 1. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Chriſt's Corporal preſence</hi> in the Sacrament. 2. To believe ſuch preſence <hi>by way of Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> 3. To <hi>adore Chriſt</hi> as being there preſent: It follows not that ſhe enjoyns the third in order to the ſecond: but may only, in order to the firſt; as the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (without the ſecond) a ſufficient ground thereof. Neither can I, disbelieving the ſecond, yet believing the firſt, refuſe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the third, that is, to worſhip the ſame object in the ſame place, as thoſe do who alſo believe the ſecond; and in my belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving both the firſt and the ſecond, yet may I nevertheleſs ground the third only on that, which is by Chriſtians more generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on; and ſtill worſhip out of no other intention, after Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation believed, than I did before I believed it (when on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I held in general a corporal preſence) or than others do; who, believing a Real preſence, do not yet believe Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>18</label> 4. Let us, then, not granting it, ſuppoſe Tranſubſtantiation an error; yet if the tenent of Corporal or Real preſence (as held by the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or others) be true, <hi>Catholicks</hi> plead, <hi>their Adoration is no way fruſtrated, but ſtill warrantable,</hi> and to be continued.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>19</label> 5<hi>ly.</hi> Suppoſe not only Tranſubſtantiation, but Real preſence an error, and the <hi>Lutheran</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick both miſtaken; yet there can be <hi>no pretence why theſe later,</hi> in ſuch Adoration, (grounded by both on Real preſence with the Symbols) <hi>will not be as excuſable from Idolatry as the other.</hi> For, thus far theſe two Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties agree: 1. That <hi>Chriſt is corporally preſent:</hi> 2. That <hi>he may be worſhipped:</hi> 3. That <hi>no other there but He may be worſhipped;</hi> not Bread, nor any other meer creature: 4. That <hi>nothing viſible in the Sacrament is He, or his Body;</hi> which is preſent only inviſibly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing viſible, inhering, or appertaining to it, as the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject thereof. They differ only about the manner of the preſence of this inviſible Subſtance. The one ſaith, it is there together with the Bread; the other ſaith there, inſtead of the Bread, and the Bread away; a thing alſo to God poſſible, for any thing we know. The one ſaith, he is there both under the ſubſtance and accidents
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63863:15"/>of Bread; the other, there under the accidents only of the bread. Now, whilſt both worſhip the ſame Object in the ſame place, and veiled with the ſame ſenſible accidents, if the one adoring him as being under the ſubſtance of bread, (he not being there) are freed from any Idolatry in ſuch worſhip; the other adoring him as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the accidents of bread, (he not being there) cannot be made hereby Idolaters: ſince they ſay, and freely profeſs, that, if his body be not there, under thoſe appearances, but the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſtill under them which was formerly; then they confeſs it a creature, and renounce all adoration of it.</p>
            <p>Whereas therefore it is objected, That the ſubſtance of bread only being in that place, where they ſuppoſe Chriſt's Body, and not any Bread, to be, therefore in worſhipping the thing in that place, they worſhip bread; this were a right charge, if they affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that they worſhipped the ſubſtance that is in that place un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch accidents <hi>whatever</hi> it be: but this none ſay; but, that they worſhip it only upon ſuppoſition that it is Chriſt's Body, and not bread, and that for this ſuppoſition they have a rational ground, (of which by and by.) Now, ſaying they worſhip it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo, is ſaying, if it be not ſo, they intend no worſhip to it. He that ſaith, I give divine Adoration to that which is under the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Bread, becauſe believed by me, or, if you will, certainly known by me (but he, indeed, miſtaking) to be Chriſt's Body, and ſo Chriſt preſent, is yet far from ſaying, I worſhip whatever is under the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Bread, whether it be Chriſt's Body or no. And he that ſaith the later of theſe, if bread happen to be there, is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly granted an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; but not ſo the former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daille,</hi> as it much concerns him, excuſeth a <hi>Lutheran</hi> adoring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a falſly ſuppoſed real or corporal preſence of our Lord, from any Idolatry, for this reaſon: Becauſe, ſaith he,<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Reply to Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> p. 63.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch adoration is miſtaken not in this,</hi>—<hi>that it addreſſeth it ſelf to an Object not ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but only that by error it ſeeks and thinks to enjoy it in a place where it is not, and ſo he ſaith it becomes only</hi> vain and unprofitable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is ſaid before §. 8. The ſame therefore muſt he allow to <hi>Catholicks,</hi> if meaning nothing more by their Language of <hi>Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Sacramenti</hi> than <hi>Chriſti in Sacramento;</hi> as hath been ſhewed before §. 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they do not: and that the contention about this is a meer <hi>Logomachy;</hi> and that they alſo, as the others, ground their Adoration not on Tranſubſtantiation, but Corporal Preſence.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>20</label> As for <hi>Coſterus,</hi> or perhaps ſome other <hi>Roman</hi> Writers, that ſay, if Tranſubſtantiation [<hi>where alſo they muſt mean,</hi> or a Corporal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63863:16"/>
               <hi>ſome other way</hi>] were not true, the Idolatry of Heathens is much more excuſable, than of Chriſtians, that worſhip a bit of bread: they do not, or at leaſt are not neceſſitated to grant the conſequence neceſſary, that, if Tranſubſtantiation or Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Preſence fail, then they muſt adore the bread; which bread mean while they deny alſo to be there: no more than <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do or think themſelves neceſſitated to grant this conſequence, That if Conſubſtantiation or Corporal Preſence fail, then the <hi>Lutherans</hi> do adore the Bread; which bread alſo tho' the <hi>Lutherans</hi> affirm to be there, yet do other Proteſtants deny that the <hi>Lutherans</hi> worſhip. But <hi>Coſterus,</hi> and others, only maintain this: That, ſuppoſing that which is impoſed upon them, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Catholicks,</hi> if there be no Tranſubſtantiation, do worſhip a bit of bread; the Heathen Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, in their worſhipping a golden or ſilver Image, or ſome li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving creature, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would be far more tolerable, and more noble. Shewing by this (as Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>Liberty of Propheſying,</hi> p. 258.) <hi>That they are ſo far from worſhipping the bread in ſuch caſe, that themſelves profeſs it to be Idolatry to do ſo; and intending, by advancing this fault the higher, the more, to make appear the impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of ſuch an error, its for ſo many hundred years poſſeſſing the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Church of Chriſt, aſſiſted by our Saviour to the end of the World, and the Pillar of Truth: and thinking the greatneſs of this crime a good argument of the Churches innocency therein; whilſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, in ſome ſmaller matters, ſhe might be liable to a miſtake. I do believe</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Thorndike, Epilog.</hi> 3. l. 30. c. p. 353.) <hi>that it hath been ſaid by great Doctors of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>that they must needs think themſelves flat Idolaters, if they could think that the Elements are not aboliſhed: That ſhews with what confidence they would have the World apprehend, that they hold their opinion; but not, that the conſequence is true; unleſs that which I have ſaid be reprovable.</hi> And again, in <hi>Juſt weights</hi> c. 19.—<hi>When they ſay they muſt be flat Idolaters, if the Elements be there, zeal to their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion makes them ſay more than they ſhould ſay.</hi>—Laſtly, <hi>If Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterus</hi> ſaith, that Tranſubſtantiation failing, Catholicks do wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the bread, <hi>Bellarmin de Eucha.</hi> l. 4. c. 30. and others, ſay juſt the contrary, arguing thus concerning a Catholick's worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping an unconſecrated Hoſt, which is nothing but bread,—<hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio ex intentione</hi> [i. e. ſuch as is rationally grounded] <hi>potiſſimum pendet. Quare qui</hi> [talem] <hi>panem adorat, quod certo credat non eſſe panem ſed Chriſtum, is proprie &amp; formaliter Chriſtum adorat, non panem.</hi> Which may as well be ſaid of an Hoſt conſecrated, that is not Tranſubſtantiated (when the adorer upon probable grounds
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63863:16"/>believes it to be ſo,) but remains ſtill bread,—<hi>Qui hunt panem adorat, quod certo credat non eſſe panem, ſed Chriſtum, is proprie &amp; formaliter Chriſtum adorat, non panem.</hi> And the ſame, much-what, as by <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> is ſaid by Dr. <hi>Hammond, Diſc. of Idolatry,</hi> §. 64. <hi>That, ſuppoſing their error be grounded on an honeſt and blameleſs miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding of Scripture, it is, tho' material, yet perhaps in them not formal Idolatry; becauſe, if they were not verily perſwaded that it were God, they profeſs they would never think of worſhipping it.</hi> Thus he.</p>
            <p>This in the 5th. place of not only Tranſubſtantiation, but Real Preſence being ſuppoſed an error, yet that the <hi>Roman</hi> practice, or error, compared with the <hi>Lutheran,</hi> the firſt is no more peccant than the later; and therefore that the <hi>Lutheran</hi> by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> being excuſed from Idolatry, ſo ought the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> too.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>21</label> 6. Both theſe being ſuppoſed errors, and indeed no Preſence of Chriſt's Body with the Symbols at all, as is by them both imagined there; yet, <hi>ſuch Adoration,</hi> by the one or the other, of <hi>Christ,</hi> who is a true object of ſupreme Adoration, and only by them miſtaken to be in ſome place where he is not, <hi>cannot be termed any ſuch Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as is the worſhipping of an object not at all adorable.</hi> So, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, If we ſuppoſe a Heathen worſhipping a Heathen-God, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome particular reſidence in an Image; or an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the true God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as having a ſpecial reſidence in the Calf at <hi>Sinai;</hi> or in <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Calves, called alſo by him <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims;</hi> or laſtly, a <hi>Manichean,</hi> miſtaking nothing in the Nature or Attributes of our Lord Chriſt, ſave that he thinks him to have ſome particular reſidence in the Sun, and ſo worſhipping him as preſent there: None of theſe would be any ſuch Idolatry, or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to it, as that of another Heathen worſhipping the very Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Image; or <hi>Iſraelite</hi> worſhipping the very Calf for his God; or <hi>Manichean</hi> worſhipping the Sun it ſelf for Chriſt. Again; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any of theſe that adore only God or Chriſt as ſpecially preſent where indeed he is not, (<hi>e. g.</hi> as fancied God ſo preſent in the Calf, or Chriſt in the Sun,) if we ſuppoſe ſomething elſe inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and undiſcerned by him to be there preſent, as if we imagine an Angel in the Sun, or a Serpent within the Calf, therefore be ſaid to adore ſuch Angel, or Serpent: and whatever fault may be in ſuch worſhip, yet it would be great injuſtice to accuſe ſuch <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite</hi> or <hi>Manichean,</hi> of adoring ſuch Angel or Serpent upon this inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Propoſition, that <hi>he profeſſeth to worſhip that which he believes to be preſent there;</hi> eſpecially if ſuch perſon do alſo declare againſt the adoration of any ſuch particular things, if, contrary to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63863:17"/>there preſent. Neither then can it be juſtly deduced from a <hi>Lutheran</hi>'s or <hi>Catholick</hi>'s adoring Chriſt as under the ſubſtance or <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Bread, that therefore theſe adore the thing it ſelf that is preſent under them.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>22</label> 7. Whatever fault or alſo Idolatry it may be called (tho' not ſo groſs as the former) in a <hi>Manichean</hi> that worſhips Chriſt in the Sun, or in an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> that worſhips God as ſpecially preſent or reſident in the Calves of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> or that at <hi>Sinai,</hi> becauſe it is adoring a fancy of their own, without any rational ground or pretence thereof; and however meerly a good intention ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a culpable ignorance can excuſe none from Idolatry, or any other fault, (which as it is often preſſed by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> is free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly granted by <hi>Catholicks.</hi>) Yet ſince <hi>Daille</hi> (and, I ſuppoſe, other Proteſtants with him) doth allow, not an abſolutely certain, but a reaſonable, tho' miſtaken ground or motive of Adoration, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for avoiding the juſt imputation of Idolatry, [upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count a Diſciple adoring with divine worſhip a perſon very much reſembling our Saviour, when he was upon Earth; or, ſuppoſing a conſecrated Hoſt truly adorable, one, who adores an Hoſt placed on the Altar, and by ſome deficiency in the Prieſt, not truly conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, is freely abſolved by them herein from committing any Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. See before §. 8.] Hence therefore if <hi>Catholicks can produce a rational ground of their apprehending Christ preſent in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist,</hi> tho' poſſibly miſtaken in it, <hi>they are to be excuſed from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> upon the ſame terms.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>23</label>(1.) Now here firſt; the <hi>Lutherans</hi> being allowed to have ſuch a plauſible ground or motive for their Adoration, whereby they become by other <hi>Proteſtants</hi> abſolved from Idolatry in adoring our Lord as preſent there, (only their Adoration <hi>inutile</hi> (ſaith <hi>Daille</hi>) <hi>&amp; tombent en neant,</hi>) I ſee not why the ground of <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> ſhould be any whit leſs valued than theirs. For, if we compare the one's Con—with the other's Trans—ſubſtantiation, the later ſeems more agreeable to our Lord's words, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum;</hi> and to the moſt plain literal obvious ſenſe thereof, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum,</hi> by a change of the Bread, rather than, <hi>Hoc est Corpus meum,</hi> by a conjunction with the Bread; and therefore is the <hi>Roman</hi> equalled with, or elſe preferred before, the <hi>Lutheran</hi> ſenſe by many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, that are neutral and diſſent from both. [<hi>Longius Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiatorum</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Forbes, de Euchar. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4 §. 5.) <hi>quam Tranſubſtantiatorum ſententiam a Chriſti verbis recedere, ſive litera ſpectetur, ſive ſenſus, affirmat R.</hi> Hoſpinianus <hi>&amp; caeteri</hi> Calviniani <hi>communiter.</hi> And <hi>Hoſpinian. Hiſtor. Sacram.</hi> 2. <hi>part. fol.</hi> 6. ſaith
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63863:17"/>of <hi>Luther,</hi>—<hi>Errorem errore commutavit, nec videns ſuam opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem non habere plus, imo etiam minus coloris, quam Scholaſticorum &amp; Papae.</hi> And ſee the ſame judgment of the <hi>Helvetian</hi> Miniſters, and <hi>Calvin, apud Hoſpinian. f.</hi> 212.] But next; <hi>Catholicks</hi> found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Adoration not on Tranſubſtantiation, but on Corporal Preſence, the ſame common ground of this they have with <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans,</hi> viz. <hi>our Lord's words implying;</hi> and ſo it muſt excuſe both, or neither.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>24</label>(2.) Laying aſide this compariſon, let us view more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what <hi>rational ground</hi> Catholicks exhibit of this their belief of a Corporal Preſence in the Euchariſt, and ſo of Adoration.</p>
            <p n="1">I. This their Ground then of ſuch a Corporal Preſence in the Euchariſt (after a poſſibility thereof, granted alſo by ſober Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants<note n="*" place="margin">See Guide in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, Diſc. 1. §. 62.</note>) is pretended to be <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> and if it be ſo as pretended, then no argument from our ſenſes, and againſt it, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid:) and that (as was ſaid but now) taken in its moſt plain, lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, natural, and grammatical ſenſe, in the words, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum;</hi> ſo often iterated in the Goſpel, and again by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any variation or change, or explication of that which yet is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by <hi>Calvinists</hi> to be a metaphorical expreſſion; and ſuch, if we will believe them, as this, that the <hi>Church is his Body,</hi> Eph. 1.23. or, <hi>He the true Vine,</hi> Joh. 15.1. A great argument this, (the Apoſtles punctual retaining ſtill, in their expreſſing the Inſtitution thereof, the ſame language and words) that our Lord intended it literally, as he ſpoke it. Pretended alſo to be Divine Revelation from many other Scriptures, (the citing and preſſing of which takes up all <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi>'s firſt Book <hi>de Euchariſtia,</hi> to which I refer the inquiſitive Reader:) but eſpecially from the Diſcourſe <hi>Jo.</hi> 6. Which Apoſtle writing his Goſpel ſo late, when the Communion of our Lord's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood was ſo much frequented and celebrated in the Church, ſeems therefore to have omitted the mention of it at all in his ſtory of the Paſſion, and the time of its firſt Inſtitution: becauſe he had dilated ſo much upon it before in relating a Sermon of our Lord's made in <hi>Gallilee</hi> about the time of the yearly Feaſt of eating the Paſchal Lamb, <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—<hi>The literal and gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical ſenſe of which Divine Revelation</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Taylor, Liberty of Propheſying,</hi> §. 20. <hi>p.</hi> 258.) <hi>if that ſenſe were intended, would war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> Catholicks <hi>to do violence to all the Sciences in the circle. And that Tranſubſtantiation is openly and violently againſt natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, would be no argument to make them disbelieve; who believe the myſtery of the Trinity in all thoſe niceties of explication which are in the Schools, (and which now adays paſs for the Doctrine of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63863:18"/>the Church,)</hi> [or he might have ſaid, which are in the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed,] <hi>with as much violence to the principles of natural and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Philoſophy, as can be imagined to be in the point of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</hi> And elſewhere (<hi>Real Preſence,</hi> p. 240.) ſaith, as who will not ſay?—<hi>That if it appear, that God hath affirmed Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, he for his part will burn all his Arguments againſt it, and make publick Amends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>25</label> II. Again; <hi>Catholicks</hi> have for their <hi>Rational ground</hi> of following this ſenſe, in oppoſition to any other given by Sectaries, the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> of it by the moſt Supreme and Univerſal <hi>Church-Authority</hi> that hath been aſſembled in former times for the deciſion of this controverſie long before the birth of <hi>Proteſtantiſm;</hi> a brief account of which Councils, to the number of ſeven or eight (if the 2d. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> [<hi>Act.</hi> 6. <hi>tom.</hi> 3.] be reckoned with the reſt) before that of <hi>Trent,</hi> all agreeing in the ſame ſentence, ſee concerning the <hi>Guide in Controverſy, Diſc.</hi> 1. §. 57, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> [Out of the number of which Councils ſaid to eſtabliſh ſuch a Doctrine, as Biſhop <hi>Coſins, Hiſt. Tranſub.</hi> c. 7. p. 149. after many others, hath much laboured to ſubduct the great <hi>Lateran</hi> Council under <hi>Innocent</hi> 3. upon pretence of the reputed Canons thereof their being <hi>propoſed</hi> therein <hi>only by the Pope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations of preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment. §. 31. <hi>p.</hi> 165.</note> but <hi>not paſſed</hi> or confirmed <hi>by the Council;</hi> ſo another late <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Writer upon another Proteſtant intereſt, <hi>viz.</hi> out of the 3d. Canon of the ſame Council, <hi>charging</hi> not only the <hi>Pope</hi> but the <hi>Councils</hi> themſelves, and the <hi>Catholick</hi> Religion, as <hi>invading the Rights of Princes,</hi> hath with much diligence very well vindicated theſe Canons againſt the others, as the true Acts of this Great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and not only the deſigns of the Pope; and copiouſly ſhewed them (as in truth they were) owned as ſuch, both in the ſame, and the following times. And thus the Doctrine of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation in this Council is firmly eſtabliſhed, whilſt <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> contend, in the other Canon concerning <hi>Secular Powers,</hi> the Senſe of the Council is by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Now upon this, I ask what more <hi>reaſonable</hi> or <hi>ſecure</hi> courſe in matters of Religion, (whether as to <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Practice</hi>) can a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and truly humble Chriſtian take, than, where the ſenſe of a Divine Revelation is diſputed, to ſubmit to that interpretation thereof, which the Supremeſt Authority in the Church, that hath been heretofore convened about ſuch matters, hath ſo often and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in the ſame manner decided to him; and ſo to act according to its Injunctions?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>26</label> III. But, if theſe Councils be declined as not being ſo ancient as ſome may expect; <hi>i. e.</hi> not held before ſome controverſy hapned
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63863:18"/>in the Church touching the point they decided, <hi>Catholicks</hi> ſtill have another very <hi>Rational ground</hi> of ſuch a ſenſe of the Divine Writ, <hi>viz. the evident teſtimony of the more Primitive times.</hi> Which that they have conveyed the Tradition of ſuch a ſenſe to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church, and to theſe former Councils, (to repeat what hath been ſaid already in <hi>Conſiderations</hi> on the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> §. 321. <hi>n.</hi> 1. becauſe perhaps by ſcarcity of copies that Book may come to few hands) I think will be clear to any one, not much intereſſed, that ſhall at his leiſure ſpend a few hours in a publick Library to read, entire, and not by quoted parcels, the diſcourſes on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; Of St. <hi>Ambroſ. de Myſter, init. cap.</hi> 9.—the Author <hi>de Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis,</hi> aſcribed to the ſame Father, 4. <hi>l.</hi> 4, and 5. Chapters.—<hi>Cyril. Hieroſol. Catecheſ. Myſtagog.</hi> 4, <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.—<hi>Chryſoſt in Matt. Hom.</hi> 83.—<hi>In Act. Hom.</hi> 21.—<hi>In</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. Hom.</hi> 24.—<hi>Greg. Niſſen. Orat. Catechet. ch.</hi> 36, 37.—<hi>Euſeb. Emiſſen.</hi> or <hi>Caeſarius Arelatenſis de Paſchate, Serm.</hi> 5.—<hi>Hilarius Pictav. de Trinitate,</hi> the former part of the 8th. Book.—<hi>Cyril. Alexand. in Evangel. Joan. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 13. Concerning the authenticalneſs of which pieces enough alſo hath been ſaid elſewhere.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>27</label> IV. In a conſequence of, and ſucceſſion from, this doctrine of thoſe Primitive times, and of the later Councils of the Church, when this Point was brought into ſome Diſpute and Controverſie, a Catholick hath for a <hi>Rational ground</hi> of his Faith, and practice, <hi>the univerſal doctrine and practice of the later</hi> both Eaſtern and Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern <hi>Churches</hi> till <hi>Luther</hi>'s time, and at the <hi>preſent</hi> alſo, excepting his followers. For the Eaſtern Churches (diſputed by ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants) both their belief of a <hi>corporal preſence</hi> with the Symbols, and practice of <hi>Adoration,</hi> ſee what hath been ſaid at large in the <hi>Guide in Controverſy, diſc.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. (where alſo are exhibited the teſtimonies of many learned Proteſtants freely conceding it) and again, in <hi>Conſiderations</hi> on the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> §. 321. <hi>n.</hi> 22. <hi>p.</hi> 313. and <hi>n.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 294. See alſo the late eminent evidences of the Faith and Practice of theſe Eaſtern Churches at this day, collected by Monſieur <hi>Arnaud,</hi> in his two replies to <hi>Claude;</hi> a brief account whereof alſo is given in the <hi>Guide, Diſc.</hi> 3. §. 81. <hi>n.</hi> 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which matter (whereas one of the chiefeſt and commoneſt Pleas of Proteſtants is the Greek and Eaſtern Churches their according with them, whereby they ſeem to out-number the Roman) if any will but take the courage, notwithſtanding his ſecular Intereſt, candidly to examin it, I doubt not he will receive a full Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63863:19"/>
            <p> Laſtly, ſee D. <hi>Blondel</hi> (one much eſteemed by Proteſtants, for his knowledge in ancient Church-Hiſtory) granting an alteration in the Doctrine concerning our Lord's Preſence in the Euchariſt (an Alteration he means from that which is now maintained by Proteſtants, and was by the former Antiquity) begun in the <hi>Greek</hi> Church after <hi>A. D.</hi> 754.<note n="*" place="margin">Eſclaire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſements ſur L' Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtie <hi>c. 15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> begun ſo ſoon as any diſpute hapned in the Eaſtern Church concerning this <hi>Preſence;</hi> which diſpute was firſt occaſion'd there upon an Argument which was taken from the Euchariſt, and urged againſt Images by the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> under <hi>Constantius Copronymus,</hi> and was contradicted by <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> and ſhortly by the 2d. <hi>Nicene</hi> Council. In which opinion of the 2d. <hi>Nicene</hi> Council and <hi>Damaſcen, Blondel</hi> freely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth the Greek Churches to have continued to this day. See <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>p.</hi> 399. Again, granting an Alteration in the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (as is ſaid before) begun in the Weſtern Church <hi>A. D.</hi> 818.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See. Ibid.</hi> c. 18.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> as ſoon as the like diſpute hapned about this Point in the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Parts: which diſpute there was occaſioned by the Council held at <hi>Frankfort</hi> under <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> oppoſing the expreſſions of the foreſaid <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> Council in like manner as the 2d. <hi>Nicene</hi> Council had done before. Laſtly, if we ask him, what this Alteration in the Eaſt firſt, and afterward in the Weſt, was; 1. He maketh it much-what the ſame in both. And then he explains it to be a kind of Impanation, or Conſubſtantiation, or Aſſumption of the Bread by our Lord Chriſt. His words, <hi>c.</hi> 19. are theſe <hi>Des l' An.</hi> 818. &amp;c.—<hi>Some among the</hi> Latins <hi>did</hi> (<hi>as it were in imitation of the</hi> Greek) <hi>conceive a kind of Conſubſtantiation, partly like, partly unlike, to what many</hi> Germains [he means Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans] <hi>now maintain; which, to ſpeak properly, ought to be called</hi> Impanation, <hi>or Aſſumption of the Bread by the</hi> Word <hi>of</hi> God. And c. 20. he goes on,—<hi>The opinion of</hi> Paſchaſius, [whom he makes Leader in the Weſtern, as <hi>Damaſcen</hi> in the Greek Church] <hi>had advanced before</hi> A. D. 900. <hi>an Impanation of the</hi> Word, <hi>fortified and getting credit by degrees; the eſtabliſhment of which</hi> (ſaith he p. 440.) <hi>both</hi> Damaſcen <hi>and</hi> Paſchaſius <hi>deſigned.</hi> Wherein (he ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 441.) they ſuppoſed a kind of Identity between the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Natural Body of Chriſt, founded upon the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Deity in them; which at laſt produced, he ſaith, the eſtabliſhment of Tranſubſtantiation, under Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third.</p>
            <p>Here then 1. We ſee granted, both of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Church, the ſame Tenent. 2. We may obſerved, that this Tenent of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panation</hi> he impoſeth on them, when well examined, is found
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63863:19"/>much more groſs and abſurd than that of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> For which ſee what is ſaid in <hi>Bellarmin, de Euchar. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13. &amp; 15. Or in <hi>Suarez, de Sacrament. Diſp.</hi> 49. But 3. ſee in <hi>Conſiderations on the Council of Trent</hi> §. 321. <hi>n.</hi> 13. and <hi>n.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that this Doctrine of <hi>Damaſcen</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, and afterwards of <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> and the <hi>Latin,</hi> before <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Third</hi>'s time, was plain Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation; and is miſrepreſented by <hi>Blondel</hi> for Impanation; and therefore never hath the <hi>Greek</hi> Church hitherto had any conteſt or claſhing with the <hi>Roman</hi> concerning this point. And ſee the conceſſions alſo of other Proteſtants very frequent and more candid, of Tranſubſtantiation held by the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches of later times, as well as by the <hi>Roman,</hi> produced in the <hi>Rational Account concerning the Guide in Controverſies,</hi> Diſc. 3. c. 8. 4<hi>ly.</hi> Laſtly, theſe Churches, in which, he ſaith, ſuch an Alteration was made from the former Doctrine of Antiquity, deny it at all ſo to be; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that, when ſome new opinions appeared, they maintained and vindicated it as the Doctrine of the Fathers; their Proofs of it being alſo extracted out of the Fathers Teſtimonies. Now then to ſtand againſt ſuch a ſtrong ſtream of both Eaſt and Weſt run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning conſtantly in this courſe, ſeems to Catholicks, with S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> very unreaſonable.—<hi>Similiter etiam</hi> (ſaith he, Epiſt. 118. Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuario) <hi>ſiquid horum tota per orbem frequentat Eccleſia: nam &amp; hinc, quin ita faciendum ſit, diſputare, inſolentiſſimae inſaniae eſt.</hi> And,—<hi>Graeci omnes</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Forbes, de Euchar.</hi> l. 2. c. 2.) [as well as the <hi>Roman</hi> Church] <hi>adorant Chriſtum in Euchariſtia: Et quis auſit omnes hos Chriſtianos Idololatriae arceſſere &amp; damnare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ſect. </seg>28</label> V. Laſtly; beſides this great Body, Catholicks have ſince <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>'s time, in the Reformation, no ſmall number of Proteſtants, I mean ſuch as are the genuine Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding thus far, as to confeſs both a <hi>Real</hi> Preſence of our Lord's Body and Blood in the Euchariſt, and <hi>Adoration</hi> of it as preſent there; a real preſence of it to each worthy Receiver, tho' not to the Elements. And <hi>Hooker,</hi> if he miſtook not the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in his time, ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ. Pol.</hi> l. 5. §. 67.—<hi>Wherefore ſhould the world continue ſtill diſtracted, and rent with ſo many manifold Contentions, when there remaineth now no Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, ſaving only about the ſubject where Chriſt is?</hi>—<hi>Nor doth any thing reſt doubtful in this, but whether, when the Sacrament is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, Chriſt be whole within Man only, or elſe his Body and Blood be alſo externally ſeated in the very conſecrated Elements themſelves.</hi> So that, if <hi>Hooker</hi> and his party are int he right, Catholicks do not miſtake Chriſt's Body as preſent in a place where it is not; but
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63863:20"/>only in thinking it in that preſent to one thing, the Elements, when it is ſo only to another, the Receiver of them. But then the ſame Catholicks have another half of the Reformation, <hi>viz.</hi> all the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Proteſtants, that affirm, with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, Chriſt's Body preſent alſo to the Elements, or Symbols. And ſee Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> alſo, <hi>Epilog. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. much for this preſence of Chriſt's Body to be <hi>in, with,</hi> or <hi>under</hi> the Elements, immediately upon, and by the conſecration of them, (which conſecration alſo he placeth (<hi>l.</hi> 3.4. <hi>c. p.</hi> 24.) in the bleſſing of the Elements before the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> mentioned before §. 7.). Look back now upon all theſe Pleas of Catholicks, and ſee if they will not make up at leaſt a <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ground</hi> or motive of their Adoration. A reaſonable ground; I ſay not here (what I might) ſufficient to ſecure their faith from all ſuſpicion of error, but (which ſerves my purpoſe) to ſecure them from Idolatry in their Adoration, tho' they ſhould be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken; when as other perſons, becauſe proceeding on like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable motives, are by Proteſtants, in their Adoration of a miſtaken Preſence, or Object, excuſed from it; (See before §. 8.) As, for example, the <hi>Lutheran;</hi> the Adorer of one much reſembling our Lord here on Earth; the Adorer of an unconſecrated Hoſt, or Wafer placed on the Altar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> eſpecially when Catholicks in crediting ſuch divine Revelation of Chriſt's Preſence, and ſo for their Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, receive no contradiction (as it is pretended they do) from their ſenſes: becauſe they adore, I mean with divine Adoration, nothing viſible, or ſenſible at all, nor any ſubſtance inviſible wherein any thing that occurs to their ſenſes inheres; but only underſtand Chriſt's Body preſent thee, where their ſenſes can no way certainly, and againſt any pretended divine Revelation, inform them, either when it is preſent, or not; ſince <hi>ſalvis omnibus phaenomenis,</hi> all appearances granted moſt true, ſuch a Preſence is poſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ſect. </seg>29</label> Theſe rational Grounds of <hi>Catholicks</hi> for Adoration, which we expected ſhould have been moſt ſtrictly examined by thoſe who conclude the <hi>Roman</hi> practice herein Idolatry, are ſlightly paſſed over by <hi>Daille,</hi> in pronouncing that this error of Catholicks <hi>vient toute entiere de leur paſſion,</hi> Apolog. des Eglis Reform. c. 11. p. 90. And after in reducing all their ground thereof to a—<hi>la ſeule au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorite du Pape &amp; de ſon Concile:</hi> and by Dr. <hi>Taylor, Real Preſ.</hi> §. 13. <hi>p.</hi> 346. in calling them—<hi>ſome trifling pretences made out of ſome ſayings of the Fathers.</hi> Elſewhere indeed, when he was in a more charitable temper (<hi>Liberty of Propheſ. p.</hi> 258.) he ſaith, <hi>That for a motive to ſuch an opinion,</hi> Roman Catholicks <hi>have a divine Revelation, whoſe literal and grammatical Senſe, if that Senſe was
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63863:20"/>intended, would warrant them to do violence to all the Sciences in the Circle:</hi> but prudently there omits their Plea of <hi>Catholick Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſecuring to them ſuch a literal ſenſe of the Text. Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi> (<hi>Rom. Idol.</hi> c. 2. §. 7.) ſaith firſt,—<hi>That, if a miſtake in this caſe will excuſe the</hi> Romaniſt, <hi>it would excuſe the groſſeſt Idolatry in the World.</hi> And in comparing two perſons, one worſhipping Chriſt as really preſent in the Sun, another, Chriſt as really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Sacrament, he ſaith, as inconſiderately as magiſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,—<hi>That ſuppoſing a miſtake in both, we are not to enquire into the reaſons of the miſtake,</hi> [i. e. as he ſaith before, concerning the probability of the one miſtake, more than of the other] <hi>but the influence it hath upon our actions.</hi> So he. But, what is more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, than that the influence which a miſtake hath upon our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to making them culpable or innocent, is not always the ſame; but very various, and often contrary; rendring them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times blameleſs, ſometimes faulty, according as the miſtake is ex-or in—exuſable? Next, he grants <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 5. a <hi>Catholick Tradition of Tranſubſtantiation</hi> to be a ſufficient ground for Adoration: But the Catholick Tradition that is pleaded here neceſſary for Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is only that of a <hi>corporal</hi> Preſence. Now, for a ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſuch a Tradition, I refer the conſciencious Reader to what hath been ſaid before, waving that of Tranſubſtantiation as to this Controverſy, tho' the ſame Catholick Tradition authorizeth both; namely, a corporal Preſence by a mutation of the Elements into our Lord's Body. This from §. 24. <hi>Of the Rational grounds Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks have for their Adoration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ſect. </seg>30</label> 8<hi>ly.</hi> For ſuch <hi>Rational grounds</hi> thereofre of their worſhip as are here given (and <hi>not</hi> from any <hi>exceſs of Charity,</hi> or from the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Fancies</hi> of ſome few, tho' learned men, as Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> in his Preface to <hi>Roman Idolatry</hi> would inſinuate) <hi>Idolatry is by many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> of late, either <hi>not at all,</hi> or but <hi>faintly charged on the Church of</hi> Rome. For firſt, ſee Mr. <hi>Thorndike</hi> in his <hi>Epilogue,</hi> 3. l. 30. c. p. 350.—<hi>I ſay firſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Adoration of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, which the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>preſcribeth, is not neceſsarily Idolatry. I ſay not, what it may be accidentally by that intention which ſome men may conceal, and may make it Idolatry as to God: but I ſpeak upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of that intention, which the profeſſion of the Church formeth.</hi> And in his <hi>Juſt Weights,</hi> c. 19. p. 125.—<hi>They who give the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour proper to God to his Creature, are Idolaters; they that worſhip the Hoſt give the honour due to God to his Creature: this is taken for a</hi> Demonſtration, <hi>that the worſhip of the Hoſt is Idolatry. But will any Papiſt acknowledge, that he honours the Elements of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63863:21"/>or, as he thinks, the Accidents of them for God? Will common Reaſon charge him to honour that, which he believes not to be there? If they were there, they would not take them for God; and therefore they would not honour them for God: And that is it</hi> (<hi>not</hi> ſaying <hi>that they ſhould be Idolaters if the Elements did remain) that muſt make them Idolaters.</hi> And <hi>Epilogue</hi> p. 357. in general he ſaith;—<hi>Whoſo admits Idolatry,</hi> [i. e. in any point whatever] <hi>to be taught by the</hi> Roman Church, <hi>can by no means grant it to be a Church; the very being whereof ſuppoſeth the worſhip of one God, excluſive to any thing elſe.</hi> The <hi>Roman Church,</hi> then, muſt either be freed from the imputation of commanding any thing that is Idolatry, (<hi>i. e.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of a creature for God): or we muſt affirm, there to be, and to have been, no true Church of Chriſt, never ſince ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of that which they ſay is Idolatry went forth, (which no ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Proteſtant, I think, hath or dare ſay of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> ſince the beginning of the Adoration of the Euchariſt:) For what Church or Sect of Religion can be Apoſtate at all, if not a Church committing, and commanding Idolatry; even the worſhipping of a piece of Bread, which themſelves made, for that God which made them and Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>And thus Biſhop <hi>Forbes, de Euchar.</hi> l. 2. c. 2. <hi>Perperam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Romanenſibus <hi>a pleriſque Proteſtantibus objicitur, &amp; illi Idololatriae craſſiſſimae &amp; graviſſimae ab his inſimulantur &amp; damnantur; cum ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique</hi> Romanenſes, <hi>ut &amp; alii fideles, credant panem conſecratum non eſſe amplius panem, ſed corpus Chriſti; unde illi non panem adorant: ſed tantum ex ſuppoſitione, licet falſa, non tamen haeretica, aut impia, vel cum fide directe pugnante, ut ſuperiore libro oſtenſum eſt, Christi corpus, quod vere adorandum est, adorant. In Eucharistia enim men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te diſcernendum eſſe Chriſtum a viſibili ſigno docent ipſi; &amp; Chriſtum quidem adorandum eſſe, non tamen Sacramentum, quia ſpecies illae ſunt res creatae &amp; inanimes, &amp; conſequenter incapaces adorationis.</hi> And <hi>Ibid.</hi> ſhewing the <hi>Greek</hi> and Eaſtern Church, as well as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> to uſe it, he concludes, <hi>Quis auſit omnes hos Chriſtianos Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lolatriae arceſſere &amp; damnare?</hi> After the ſame manner the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Spalato, de Repub. Eccleſ.</hi> 7. l. 11. c. n. 6.—<hi>Reſpondeo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>me nullum idololatricum crimen in adoratione Euchariſtiae, ſi recte dirigatur intentio, agnoſcere. Qui enim docent, panem non eſſe amplius panem, ſed corpus Chriſti, illi profecto panem non adorant: ſed ſolum ex ſuppoſitione, licet falſa, Chriſti corpus vere adorabile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorant. Non enim nostri dicunt ſpecies panis &amp; vini, hoc eſt, acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia illa eſſe adoranda.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63863:21"/>
            <p> Biſhop <hi>Bramhal,</hi> cited before, §. 6.—<hi>The Sacrament is to be adored, ſaid the Council of</hi> Trent. <hi>The</hi> Sacrament, i. e. <hi>formally the Body and Blood of Christ ſay ſome of your Authors: we ſay the ſame.</hi>—<hi>The</hi> Sacrament, i. e. <hi>the</hi> ſpecies <hi>of Bread and Wine ſay others: that we deny.</hi> Thus he.</p>
            <p>D. <hi>Taylor,</hi> in his <hi>Liberty of Propheſying,</hi> p. 258. confeſſeth the Subjects of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> no Idolaters in this kind; at leaſt ſo as to worſhip Bread or any creature with Divine Worſhip, and as God: For,—<hi>It is evident,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the</hi> Object <hi>of their Adoration (that which is repreſented to them in their minds, their thoughts, and purpoſes, and by which God principally, if not ſolely, takes eſtimate of humane actions) in the Bleſſed Sacrament, is the only true and eternal God, hypoſtatically joyned with his holy Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; which Humanity they believe actually under the veil of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental ſigns. And if they thought Him not preſent, they are ſo far from worſhipping the Bread in this caſe, that themſelves profeſs it to be Idolatry to do ſo; which is a demonſtration that their ſoul hath nothing in it that is idololatrical,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> as to the directing this their divine worſhip to an undue object.]</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>31</label> Which things if ſaid right by him and the others, the ſame Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> is faulty in his charge in <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> p. 334. Faulty I ſay, in charging on the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not their worſhip of a right Object in a ſome-way unlawful and prohibited manner, this we are not here examining; but their worſhip of an undue Object of Adoration, of a creature inſtead of God: for ſo he chargeth them there. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he there) <hi>they be deceived in their own ſtrict Article,</hi> [he means of Tranſubſtantiation,] <hi>then it is certain, they commit an act of Idolatry in giving divine honour to a mere creature, the image, the Sacrament and repreſentment of the Body of Christ.</hi> Thus he. <hi>When it is evident that the Object,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is the only true and eternal God,</hi> &amp;c. as he ſaid before in the place cited, and muſt ſay if he will ſay truth. So, faulty is alſo <hi>Daille,</hi> (<hi>Reply to Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> p. 63.) in his charging the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to worſhip Bread, upon this arguing: <hi>Catholicks adore that ſubſtance that is veiled with the accidents of Bread and Wine; but this ſubſtance is Bread:</hi> Ergo <hi>they adore Bread.</hi> By which arguing he may as well prove the <hi>Lutherans</hi> in the Euchariſt to adore a Worm or a Mire, thus: The <hi>Lutherans</hi> adore that ſubſtance which is joyned with the Bread; but that ſubſtance is a Worm or Mite: (for ſuch thing may be there with the Bread at ſuch time of Adoration) <hi>Ergo,</hi> they adore a Worm. Whereas both the <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Lutheran</hi> explain the indefinite term <hi>[that which,]</hi> uſed in the <hi>major</hi> Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63863:22"/>reſtrictively to the Body of Chriſt, and excluſively to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubſtance whatever, that is, or may be, there, either with the Bread, or under its accidents. Faulty alſo is Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet, Rom. Idol. c.</hi> 2. in ſaying the Proteſtants controverſie with Catholicks is; <hi>Whether proper Divine Worſhip, in the time of receiving the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist, may be given to the Elements on the account of a corporal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence under them,</hi> p. 117. And, as for the paſſage in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent, ſeſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 5. urged by him there for it, his miſtake is ſhewed before, §. 12. And ſo, faulty, in his concluding, <hi>p.</hi> 118.—<hi>That the immediate term of that Divine Worſhip given by</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, <hi>is the external and viſible ſigns or elements.</hi> And again, <hi>p.</hi> 124. <hi>That, upon the principles of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, no Man can be ſatisfied that he worſhips not a mere creature with divine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, when he gives Adoration to the Host:</hi> [whenas Catholicks expound themſelves to mean by Hoſt in their Adoration, not the Symbols, or <hi>Sacramentum,</hi> but <hi>rem Sacramenti.</hi>] Again, <hi>p.</hi> 125, 127, 129.—<hi>That, ſuppoſing the Divine Nature preſent in any thing, gives no ground upon that account to give the ſame worſhip to the thing wherein it is preſent.</hi>] [Catholicks grant this as much as he: and doth not himſelf ſay ſeveral times, <hi>That</hi> Catholicks <hi>condemn the worſhipping of a mere creature for Idolatry?]</hi> See §. 4. p. 120.—<hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it ſhould be but a mere creature</hi> [that I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,] <hi>all the World cannot excuſe me from Idolatry, and my own Church</hi> [he means the <hi>Roman</hi>] <hi>condemns me; all agreeing that this is groſs Idolatry.</hi> Again; <hi>p.</hi> 119. <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a principle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputable among them,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> Catholicks,] <hi>that to give proper divine honour to a creature is Idolatry.</hi> Again; <hi>p.</hi> 126. he ſaith,—<hi>he finds it generally agreed by the Doctors of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, that the Humane Nature of Christ conſidered alone,</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> without an Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical union to the Divinity,] <hi>ought not to have divine honour given to it:</hi> [and therefore neither any other creature whatever, that is not Hypoſtatically united, as none beſides It is.] All theſe, I ſay, faulty and miſtaken in charging the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with this <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Idolatry, of worſhipping a creature [<hi>the Bread]</hi> inſtead of Chriſt; from which the other Proteſtants clear it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>32</label> Laſtly, Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> §. 64. upon ſuppoſition that the ignorance or error of <hi>Catholicks</hi> is grounded on miſunderſtanding of Scripture, <hi>[I add, ſo expounded to them by the ſupreme Church-Authority,]</hi> ſeems to charge them rather with a material than a formal Idolatry; which material Idolatry in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny caſes is or may be committed without ſin; as alſo material Adultery, and the like. His words are;—<hi>That if it be demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63863:22"/>Whether in this caſe, that their ignorance or error be grounded on miſunderſtanding of Scripture, this ſo ſimple and not groſs ignornace may ſerve for a ſufficient antidote to ally the poiſon of ſuch a ſin of material, tho' perhaps in them not formal, Idolatry,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>becauſe if they were not verily perſwaded that it were God, they profeſs they would never think of worſhipping it?</hi>—<hi>he had no neceſſity to define and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie it, being only to conſider what Idolatry is; and not how excuſable ignorance or miſtake can make it.</hi> And indeed Proteſtant Writers, that will have it to be Idolatry, are concerned to make it ſuch a gentle one, as that the practice thereof, died in, and it neither particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſed, nor repented of, yet excludes not from Salvation; or elſe they muſt damn all thoſe who lived in the viſible communion of the Church <hi>Catholick</hi> for five or ſix hundred years, by their own confeſſion.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>33</label> 9. Mean-while Catholicks willingly grant to Proteſtants that, for which <hi>Daille</hi>'s Apology of the <hi>Reformed Churches, c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 98. much contendeth in their behalf: That to Adore that which the Adorer believes not to be our Lord, but Bread; or to perform the external ſigns of Adoration to our Lord as preſent there, where the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper believes he is not, is unlawful to be done by any, ſo long as the perſon continues ſo perſwaded: For, <hi>Conſcientia erronea obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat.</hi> But then, if we ſuppoſe the Church <hi>juſtly</hi> requiring ſuch Adoration upon ſuch a true Preſence of our Lord; neither will the ſame perſon be free from ſinning greatly in his following ſuch his conſcience, and in his not adoring: diſobedience to the Churches juſt commands being no light offence. Neither for the yielding ſuch obedience in general is it neceſſary that the Churches Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects be abſolutely certain of the rightneſs or lawfulneſs of the Churches Decrees or Commands: For, thus, the more ignorant in ſpiritual matters and the things commanded that any perſon is, the more free and releaſed ſhould he be from all obedience; the contrary of which is true. But ſufficient it is even in the ſtating of judicious Proteſtant Divines, when writing againſt Puritans, (ſee <hi>Conſiderations on the Council of</hi> Trent, §. 295. <hi>n.</hi> 3, 4.) that ſuch perſons be not abſolutely certain that the Churches commands are unjuſt, and that they do in ſomething demonſtratively contradict God's Law: which plain contradiction, if a private perſon can ſee it, 'tis ſtrange the Church ſhould not. And as to this particular matter, after the Churches motives of Adoration, that are deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before, §. 24, &amp;c. well conſidered, I leave the Reader to judge, whether ſuch a pretended certainty can have any ſolid ground. It is better indeed to forbear an action, when we are not certain of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63863:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>lawfulneſs thereof, provided that we are certain, that in ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance we do not ſin. But thus certain of our not ſinning in ſuch forbearance we cannot be, concerning any thing that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned us by our lawful and Canonical Superiors; whom we are obliged to obey: unleſs (as hath been ſaid) we are firſt certain that ſuch their command is unlawful.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>34</label> And hitherto of this Controverſie; where the Two main things that ſeem worthy to be examined, by any Chriſtian, who in this point ſeeks ſatisfaction, are, 1. Whether the <hi>Roman</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick's <hi>grounds</hi> of believing Chriſt's <hi>Corporal</hi> Preſence in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, with the Symbols, <hi>are ſolid and true.</hi> 2. And next; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Church, <hi>for any ones enjoying her Communion, exacts more</hi> of him, than the <hi>confeſſing</hi> that Chriſt as preſent there <hi>is</hi> alſo there to be <hi>adored:</hi> whilſt mean-while ſuch perſon renounceth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares againſt any adoration, or, if you will, co-adoration of the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or any other thing whatever there preſent, with any <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria</hi> or ſupreme worſhip, proper or improper, or with any other honour or reverence, ſave only ſuch an inferior veneration as is exhibited by us to other Holy Things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:63863:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
